about
kicking off teed up kicking off I've
already mixed a metaphor we haven't even
started yet hey Ben I have a question
this is Derek again
um does it mean anything if you don't so
when I have to when I run different
commands I have to take the the dollar
sign out does that matter or not really
yeah the dollar sign is just meant to be
um actually kind of a hint that you're
on the terminal it's not something you
actually run okay this is one of these
ancient computer programming traditions
of like the terminal begins with the
dollar sign all right okay just make it
there and there yes I probably shouldn't
even put it in the
the little code Snippets
one of the many things we assume
sometimes
car is your hand raised for help
uh I'm being helped in the chat I'll
take my hand
great
foreign
I actually have a question as well go
ahead uh so I did have all the current
versions of people B and everything and
uh and then I did uh pip and V installed
brew and for some reason it like ran all
the good and everything and then it
failed and said they erased everything
and now when I say it's MV version uh it
just says that there's no directory so I
think I messed something up Well we'd
have to get into the details of it I
suspect one of our coaches could maybe
just uh start message with you and try
to sort it out
okay thank you I bet it's not as bad as
you think
I bet you're bet you're there it may be
um a shadow copy issue so if you read
the error message it'll give you a
command to directly download from the
GitHub instead of making a shallow copy
okay
Andrea are we set
we are good to go oh I love it thank you
so much
um coaches so go ahead
okay oh yeah so again for anybody who's
joined uh we are recording this so there
will be a video if you miss any parts
great and if you don't want your little
face to show up in any way you might
want to hide your video right
yeah
okay great
teachers coaches are we ready to start
you think
I think so
all right let's do it good morning
everyone welcome
maybe somebody could help I'm still
trying to help Salma a little bit she's
still stuck well I'm gonna Spiel here
for a little while so you got some time
all right there's going to be some
painful nerdsplaining before we code
and I promise I'll keep it short okay
all right good morning everyone welcome
to First python notebook which is a
step-by-step guide to analyzing data
with python for news and this is a open
source course or curriculum that has
been developed and taught by a team of
data journalists kind of Across America
to help spread skills that we really see
as essential to doing our work and then
we want to make sure more people know
how to do
and this is a class that was first
taught maybe five or six years ago
um uh uh as an outgrowth of a of a
project called the California Civic data
Coalition which was an effort between um
some people at the LA Times the
University of Missouri Stanford and
other California news outlets to
um
to get a grip on the state of
California's kind of awful campaign
Finance database and so the materials
both cover how to do basic data analysis
in Python and also a lot of the
particulars of how to conduct an
analysis of money in California politics
and so over the next I think probably
three or four hours depending on our
Pace we're going to very carefully and
very slowly go through step by step
everything it takes to install and use
the python tools for data analysis and
and along the way
basically do the uh conducted an
interview of the data to try to develop
a story about money in politics in this
case we're going to be looking at the
money that was spent in November uh up
running up to the election of November
2016 when there was a ballot measure in
California
um that asked whether residents would
like to legalize the recreational use of
marijuana spoiler alert they said yes
and we're going to try to use these
tools to figure out who gave the most
money on each side how much was spent
and try to come up with some story ideas
along the way okay I'm joint my name is
Ben Welsh
I'm the data and graphics editor at the
Los Angeles Times where we have a team
of reporters and computer programmers
who do this type of work all day every
day to find develop and and tell stories
using data I'm joined by two fellow
teachers today my colleague Iris Lee
and Andrew suozo of propublica and over
the course of this class I'm going to
pass the mic to them to teach some other
large sections of it after I kick it off
here I'm also joined by a number of
coaches distinguished coaches from
across the country Cheryl Phillips at
Stanford uh Joe dramuska at the night
lab in Chicago or Evanston and uh Derek
Willis in in Maryland right Derek
correct uh do we have other coaches did
I overlook anyone
we have most of the time zones covered
we have most of the times that they're
very good and um
and so they're here to help if you get
stuck you know we're going to go through
this slowly
um but it and everything is entirely
fully documented we'll look at that in a
second but if you have any trouble along
the way there's a a feature in Zoom
where you're able to raise your hand and
ask for help and if you do that one of
our coaches will uh will spot it and
then kind of reach out and try to help
you solve whatever issues you have okay
um
the materials that we're going to go
through are all available at a website
that is called at
www.firstpython
notebook.org this is basically the
script for the entire class and we're
going to go through it chapter by
chapter line by line together everything
is fully documented you can copy and
paste and ought to copy and paste the
commands where appropriate into your
terminal into your notebook as we go if
if we're going too slowly you could you
could move it you could you know Skip
ahead using this if you'd like
um it's all there right this is it and
it's going to be available for you after
class is over too of course
um so I would ask everybody to open a
web browser and go to
www.firstnightfirstpythonokebook.org
just so that you have it up and you can
follow along with us as we progress
through the class so I'd ask everybody
to do that as a first step I'll give you
a second
foreign
we can maybe begin with a little bit of
an overview of all the things we're
going to cover right so we're going to
there's there's like just some jargon we
should probably get out of the way some
computer programming terms about the
tools we're using that I'd like to
demystify if possible before we begin
the first is python so python is a
computer programming language that
allows you to do really all kinds of
different things it has these very
fundamental programming tools that let
you read and write to files that let you
do mathematics that
um could let you make music if you use
it right that can do really anything
right and so it is sort of a fundamental
tool of programming that you can use to
kind of piece together scripts and
programs to kind of accomplish whatever
you want but it is very generic right
and and um and using it alone would
require writing a lot of code and using
a lot of gnarly things and so we're
going to use Python and some some
friends that make it easier for us to
install other tools and use them so that
we can write less code and things are a
little more streamlined and easy to do
okay so python is the programming
language we're going to use and we need
again python version 3.6 or higher it's
this is an open source tool that's
constantly evolving and growing and if
you have an older version some of the
tools we're going to use in class today
won't work right and so for everything
we're going to use to work you need to
have at least python version 3.6 or
higher right
that's buzzword number one buzzword
number two is pandas so pandas is a um
is a is a python tool so there's there's
there were some Bros on Wall Street who
wanted to write code to analyze the
stock market and manage their
Investments and make charts and have an
easier time doing it in Python and so
they created an open source tool called
pandas which is
just a huge hunk of python with all
these different shortcuts built in to
make life easier that allow you to read
in spreadsheets or database tables flip
them around filter them group them sort
them aggregate them right and and and
and kind of just do stuff with data and
so pandas is a python tool that makes
working with data easier and we're going
to use it for that purpose and if you've
ever heard of say for instance r or some
of these other statistical tools pandas
is sort of the Python equivalent of that
it's Python's version of a sort of data
management and analysis tool and Iris is
going to guide you through most of the
instruction of how to use pandas to do
stuff all right
our third jargony buzzword is the
Jupiter notebook which used to be called
the python notebook
the Jupiter notebook is a web browser
interface for writing code people
primarily use it to write python but you
can also use it to write r or a language
called Julia or several other different
languages and what it is is it's just a
nice friendly way to write your code
line by line and document it kind of as
you go and save it and share it and
remix it and rerun it and it has kind of
gradually become the standard for
reproducible data analysis in a lot of
the hard Sciences in Big Data operations
in Silicon Valley and is increasingly
used by journalists as a tool for um for
just like writing your code in a way
that it's just easier to deal with right
and it actually grew out of the desire
for scientific papers to be more
reproducible so if you're going to
publish a physics paper with all this
math in it for instance right how could
anyone else redo your math or check on
it or make sure it's accurate so the
Jupiter tool is a way in which you can
sort of write something like a
scientific paper that has living
breathing code in it that can be run and
rerun right and so we're gonna we're
gonna install the Jupiter notebook and
we're going to write our Python and
pandas inside of it right and along the
way we're going to see a lot of the
benefits of doing that too
right and then our third or our final
tool that we're going to install is one
called Altair
Altair is a python tool for making
charts so pandas is a python tool that's
really good at like working with data
but it's mostly good for like flipping
spreadsheets around and stuff where all
tear can take that data
and it can then help you make some cool
charts with it without a lot of work and
this is a it's a it's a pretty new tool
but it's pretty powerful as well and
it's kind of a nice way to get in there
and start sketching with your data and
drafting charts and kind of seeing
what's there and at the end of our class
today we're going to take the results of
our analysis of money in the marijuana
ballot measure race and we're going to
make some charts of them which actually
will be pretty close to stuff that that
could potentially be published and
Andrea's going to teach that part of the
class when we get there
right
um I think with that we've covered all
the buzzwords and all the all the the
nerdy like terminology I think you'll
need to know at a high level there'll be
a much more nerdy things to come but
that's like the big picture
um before we sort of kick off and just
like dive in and start writing code and
installing these tools does anybody have
any questions about the kind of Concepts
foreign
coaches teachers did I overlook anything
no okay then we're gonna Dive In so uh
let's get going so that that's our
overview we're going to begin with a
little bit of a prologue about some of
the tools that we're going to install
to do our work today right and use today
so one thing that everyone needs
to progress in this class is a command
line interface or a terminal you know
back in the days before
um the Revolutionary appearance of
Windows 3.1 you know and the user
interfaces that we're all now you know
comfortable using our computers with uh
programmers and people work with
computers spent all day on the command
line these sort of terminals issuing
little short commands back and forth
with the computer to like tell it what
to do right and that sort of old school
approach to like directly commanding
your computer is something that most
computer users never do or don't have to
do but the computer programmers do
pretty much all day because you have a
hunk of code that you want to run you
want to do something really sort of
specific and precise to your computer as
you're manipulating data or whatever
issuing these commands to the command
line is still kind of the like
um the the way that people do it and so
so to become a programmer and do this
type of work even as as a casual data
journalist does require that you become
to at least some degree familiar with
working on your com your the command
line of your computer and uh every Pro
every operating system has its own kind
of way of dealing with this and there's
a lot of different programs that can
operate as the command line but the
first thing we want everybody to do is
open up the version on their computer
and just get ready to start
telling the computer what to do and so
I'm on a Linux computer and so I have my
terminal here on the right which I hope
you can see right if you're on if you're
on an Apple computer you'll want to go
to the uh the upper right hand corner I
think where there's a magnifying glass
and you'll want to type in terminal and
then that will give you access to your
computer's command line if you're if
you're on Windows we had instructed you
to install the windows subsystem for
Linux which will create its own terminal
inside the uh the program we want to get
that up and running and I just ask
everybody now to open up their terminal
and get ready to go
and you'll see here
this sort of blinking eye of the
computer as it waits for you to tell it
what to do
so I'm going to give it a second for
everybody to get there
when you first encountered the terminal
it's a little mysterious right there's
just this sort of blinking cursor and an
empty command line and nobody really
asking you what to do or giving you any
instructions and that is uh because
these are sort of
these systems are are built to
um
they expect you to come to it knowing
what to do and be learning how to use
the command line just means gradually
learning about and practicing and using
the hundreds or thousands of little itty
bitty commands that can be used to
interact with it and no one is born
knowing these things they were mostly
invented like in the late 70s and early
80s by like sweaty nerds at like Bell
Labs or wherever and they're a little
weird and it's not your fault that
they're a little weird they just are
because of how they were created and
because of how computers have evolved
they are still with us 40 years later
and so getting comfortable doing this
and learning how to do it is just sort
of gradually embracing the process of
learning what these odd things are and
so I'm just going to start off with just
a couple of the common ones that that
are good to know and that kind of
illustrates you know how this how this
operation works so there's a command
that you'll be able to run called PWD
again pretty cryptic right so if you
type PWD and you hit enter
you can see that it's going to print out
something just below okay PWD it so
happens stands for present working
directory duh right and it's really it's
just a command that prints the current
location in the file system where you
are on the terminal and this illustrates
a key point is that whenever you're on
your command line you are also at some
position within the folder structure of
your computer from which your commands
are operated and so my term when I run
PWD
the terminal is telling me Ben you are
currently in your home folder and if I
were to open up my uh my finder on my
computer here next to my terminal you
can see that this is the user interface
that does the same thing here in my
finder it's my home folder for my user
palewire and here's all my stuff right
and so at the terminal currently my
um my user on the terminal is currently
in this folder here that you see on the
left and as we move through the class
you are navigating through the folder
structure on the terminal in the same
way that you do when you click around
inside these interfaces that I think
we're all familiar with for moving
through folders
okay
this brings us to another command this
one called LS
and LS is a command that stands for list
and it will just list everything that's
in the directory and you can see that I
have this very sort of verbose output of
like crazy things because I'm a
programmer but what this is really doing
is it is listing everything that's in my
home directory and so we can see here on
the left it says there's a pictures
folder there's a Purl five folder hell
yeah there's a videos folder right and
those correspond to the folders that are
over here in in the window and so LS is
a command that just lists everything in
your current directory and it is
effectively the same as looking at it in
the user interface on the left and so
for almost anything that you would do in
the finder open a folder move into a
folder create a folder delete a folder
rename a folder copy a folder all those
things that you would do in the user
interface there are equivalents of in
the terminal they just have like very
cryptic ancient computer programming
names for the programs that do it with
PWD being my first example and LS being
my other example
another one that might be helpful like
at this moment is there's one called
clear
if I type clear it's going to zap
everything that's in my terminal and
just bring stuff back to where we
started so it it kind of tidies things
up a little bit so those are those are
three examples
um my favorite terminal command is is
what I think of as the most existential
of all commands there's a command called
who am I and if I simply type who am I
it says back palewire which is my
username right and so this is perhaps
not a very useful command but it's one
that I enjoy
um Andrea what's your favorite terminal
command
uh
that's a good question
I think I use LS the most LS it's very
useful
I think my second favorite one is
called cow say
so there's a command called cow say and
then anything you say after that
is then broadcast by a cow
super useful I love it
what's that PG CD is a great command
that's for changing directories from
moving One Directory to another is CD
and that's the same as double clicking
on a folder in your finder and moving
into the next directory and we're going
to do that together here in a minute
Cal State is probably the best now that
I think about it
come on actually
there's one where if you mess up
I think it's called the where if
you mess up typing a command you just
type and it it guesses what your
command was supposed to be
very useful I did not know that one
okay learn something every day
uh all right very cool so we're on this
command line we're going to use it to
create folders move within them install
things and just kind of navigate through
the class
all right everybody's got that
cool uh as we know everybody needed to
have a python version installed before
they got into class today and you know
the python command on the command line
is really just the way of invoking the
Python program to run code or to do
things right so if you do python space
and then the name of a file that has a
hunk of python code in it it's going to
run that python code right and the
command that I asked everybody to run as
part of just preparing for this class is
python dash dash version which is just a
command that asks python what current
version of python is available on your
computer right and this can verify it's
there I'm going to use another command
just to show off a little bit called
witch Python and this will actually show
me where python is installed because
python itself is just like a program
that's somewhere on your computer right
and by running the which command I'm
asking my computer where is python
anyway and this actually reveals to me
this has been where your your current
python installation like is at right
like inside your file system
so Python's one
everybody should should could run python
version if you haven't already just to
make sure you've got it installed
okay
and then our other kind of uh
prerequisite and type of thing we need
to have installed is a little more
conceptually complicated but you know as
we were as I was talking about earlier
with pandas and Jupiter and Altair
um python alone is not enough to do what
we want to do right because the python
tools are so rudimentary and basic that
to conduct a more complicated data
analysis or make a chart would require
us to write a lot of python right so
there's these other python tools that
are out there in the world where helpful
open source programmers have developed
and released sort of hunks of code that
have all these shortcuts and make life
easier for you right and those are
available in a place called The Python
package index which is at Pi Pi p y p i
Dot o-r-g and this is kind of uh a phone
book of sorts of thousands probably
hundreds of thousands of little people
clumps of python that can be used to do
different things and so for instance
we're so pandas is
um an entry in the python package Index
this is actually not it sorry
um
that uh that is
um basically a offers a way for you to
download and install this this big chunk
of code that has all these shortcuts
into it onto your computer so you can
begin using pandas yourself right and
every programming language has some kind
of directory like this of helpers and
tools that you can install that are out
there on the web and every programming
language has a tool to help you do that
so basically it's a tool that helps you
install other tools right and this is
typically called a package manager right
and this is a way in which you can
basically ask your computer from the
command line to go to the phone book or
directory of packages grab the one
you're looking for and install it on
your computer right and if you've taken
like python scraping classes you've
probably learned about tools like
requests or beautiful soup right or if
you've tried to build a database website
with python you may have heard of Django
or flask these are really helpful python
tools that are out there that you would
use a package manager to get installed
on your computer so that you can take
advantage of them right and whether
you're writing node code or Ruby code or
Pearl code hell yeah or whatever else
they're going to have their own version
of a package manager to go get stuff and
get it going okay and so Pippi and V is
a package manager which everybody had to
have installed and so it has within it
everything you need to do to go get
something and get it on your computer
right so it's a package manager but it's
it is also a second thing
and the second thing it is is an
environment manager which is where the
EnV and its name comes from right and
this is this is a a more advanced
concept but
um you know these tools that we download
and install are all constantly upgrading
and constantly changing it could be in
conflict with each other or be in
conflict with the version of python we
have installed and so over time if you
just use a package manager to install
whatever you need on your computer right
the different projects that you're
working on are going to start to crash
and have problems because different code
is using different versions of programs
and things just kind of go wrong
and you can also end up in a situation
too where you might want to take your
code and have it run on someone else's
computer maybe one of your colleagues
right or maybe on a computer server that
runs in the cloud and creates a website
then when and in order to make your code
transferable from your computer to
another computer it's helpful to have a
system that is sort of like a um
a a contained little space that has
everything necessary to execute your
code so it has the version of python
that you're using it has all of the
outside packages from Pi Pi that you've
downloaded installed that has all of
their versions carefully managed and
then that way you can have this little
um like Tupperware like container that
has everything necessary to do what you
do and so people who get serious about
programming will install things in a way
so that every project that they work on
has its own little modular space with
everything necessary to be installed and
isn't dependent on other things on their
computer and the tools that do that are
called environment managers or sometimes
it's called a virtual environment and so
you're creating a sort of computer
within your computer that has everything
it needs to go right and pit bnv is also
that and so we're going to use the pippy
Envy tool to create a little container
on your computer for everything we're
going to need in class right and then
we're going to use its package managing
functions to install pandas and Jupiter
and all the stuff and all tear so that
they can run our code and execute our
analysis inside that environment and
this is a hassle right and it is
strictly speaking not 100 necessary to
get code running however it is a very
good uh code hygiene I suppose or just
the right way to program and we think
it's important enough that it should be
part of kind of a basic class like this
okay and so
that's what we're going to do with Pip
Envy here in one second and we're going
to get our hands in it and actually
install some stuff but before we do that
uh as my uh long-winded Spiel is winding
up winding down I just want to ask are
there any questions about the topics or
concepts we just covered
okay now we're going to code
spiel's over so we're going to go back
to our terminal right and again just
like I did with python version I can do
Pippi and V dash dash version to verify
that our buddy Pippi and V is installed
right so we have python we have Pippi NV
we're on our command line it's time to
get cooking so I'm going to type clear
to just clear out my terminal before we
go
um
is is my uh
is my terminal text big enough that you
guys can read it
or should I pump it up a little I'll
pump it up one step is that better
yeah that's better okay thanks uh now
um
and if if uh if I go too fast or if you
can't read anything just shout okay so
again we can use PWD to figure out where
we are we're in Ben's home directory or
in your home directory or anywhere else
before we begin
I would like to create a new directory
in which I'm going to store all of the
code that we write as part of this class
right and to do that I'm going to use a
command that we haven't used before
which is called mkdir
which is just a strange abbreviation for
make directory and so this is a tool
that will make a new folder in your
computer
all right and as you can see in the docs
we advise that you make a directory
called code to keep all of your code in
I already have a directory called code
so just to make the point I'm going to
riff and I'm going to make my directory
called mooc because we're in a mooc
right now guys all right and if I go
back to my finder in my home directory
we'll see
that there now is a folder called mooc
can you see that so because I typed
make dear mooc from my home directory
boom there's the folder right and so I
would encourage you to make your own
move or make make a code directory for
yourself and that will make a new folder
where we're going to store stuff
and then inside that folder I want to
create another folder that's just for
our class and so I'm going to do mkdir
mooc slash and then I'm going to call it
first hyphen python hyphen notebook
right and you'll see that I have a
little slash in there so I can create a
subdirectory for my current position
right now if I go back to my finder
and I look in the mooc directory
we can see that there's now is a folder
called first python notebook which we
just created and is empty all right so
everybody should do that make those
folders
we're going to use another command that
one of our students mentioned earlier to
move into the directory that we just
created and this command is called CD
which is short for change directory and
so I'm going to type CD m o o mooc I'm
going to try to go into that director
just created and here we can cover one
of the most important terminal tricks is
if you type the first few letters of
something and then you hit the Tab Key
it will auto complete what you've just
been typing see how I did that moo tab
it finished typing it for me isn't that
nice and in this case since there's only
one subdirectory I can hit tab again and
it types everything for me love it
so I'm going to do CD mooc slash first
python notebook
hit enter
and now you'll see if I type PWD again
it will say Ben you're now inside a
different directory you're now inside
first python notebook
and so if that is the same as being
inside this folder right here in my
finder so we now have positioned our
terminal inside a folder we've made
specifically for uh this class and this
is where we're going to begin using our
tools to work
if you have trouble with any of this
feel free to raise your hand and one of
our coaches can message you all right
now we're going to use pip bnv to
install our first program and we're
going to install a program that is kind
of irrelevant and not that useful just
to kind of get some practice
and understand the fundamentals of
what's going on so the I'm going to type
Pippi and V and then install which is
going to ask pipian V to install
something and then whatever I type after
install is the name of the program that
on the python package index the Pippi
and V is going to go get and try to
install right and so I'm going to
install for the purposes of this
demonstration a program called yoke 3K
and yoke 3K is
um it's just a very simple python
package that it will print out every
other package that you have installed so
it's a tool for listing all the stuff
that is installed currently within your
environment right and so it's it's it's
it's not something we're to use for our
analysis but it just helps us kind of
get the concepts oh that's wrong sorry
Pippi and V install yoke 3K is what I'm
going to type in and I know it's yoke 3K
because that's its name in the package
Index right and here's the documentation
for how it works here's here's the
command that will list all of our python
packages which we're going to try in a
minute but first we need to install it
so I'm going to do pip EnV space install
space yoke 3K hit it
now Pippi and V is going on it's first
off it's creating a new virtual
environment that we talked about earlier
so that they're inside our current
folder there was no existing virtual
environment or little modular Tupperware
to stop to store all the stuff we're
working in because it's the first time
we've run the command here so the first
thing that pit BNB did is it installed
it and it actually installs an entirely
separate version of python inside this
that will run separately from your
systems python installation
after it's done that and here's the
location of that on the on the computer
system it shows here that this virtual
environment is sort of hidden away in my
computer at this location
and then it goes off to the python
package index it looks up yoke 3K in the
phone book and it installs it so this is
successful right and then
um so it's success yes and then at the
bottom it gives me a little hint here it
says if you want to run a command inside
of your virtual environment do it with
Pip EnV run
and that's the next trick we're going to
learn is how after you've installed a
python package into your environment how
to execute it right
um and we're going to do that to run the
Yoke command that we saw in the
documentation so in the documentation
yoke said if you want to list all of
your installed python packages you
should run a command called yoke Dash L
and so I'm going to run clear to clear
out my terminal
and then I'm going to do pip EnV run and
then I'm going to run that command yoke
Dash l
and it'll take a second but you can see
it then prints out here's all the stuff
that's installed inside your virtual
environment Ben so here these are basic
python tools that are used by the
package manager that are kind of always
there and then here's the new tool that
we installed ourself yoke 3K right and
so we've now used pit BNB to create our
virtual environment we've installed our
first kind of demonstration package and
then we've been able to then run code
using that demonstration package
okay if we look inside our directory if
I run LS and hit enter
we'll now see that there are two new
files that are in our directory that
were not there before there's the PIP
file
and the PIP file lock right I'm going to
open the PIP file
real quick and say well what the heck is
this that just showed up on our computer
and this is Pippi and B's way of sort of
recording what it's doing so let's say
we want to take what's inside your
folder and we want to run it on your
colleague's computer or on a computer
server this file contains the
instructions that the pipi and V on the
other computer needs to install
everything to do
um and to do do what it needs to do and
run your code and so we can see here
that it includes a list of installed
packages
like yoke 3K which we just installed it
has my version of python Etc
for what we're doing today there's no
reason you need to look at this file or
do anything with it but it's good to
know that this kind of exists this is
what's known as a manifest file and it's
just the list of everything you need to
run your code right and the lock is sort
of a more sophisticated version of this
file that is intended for the computer
to read not for us the humans so when
you add or subtract different programs
the human would do it in the pivot file
and then the PIP file lock will be
updated by Pippi NV so that the computer
can keep up to speed with what you're
doing
okay
um and with that we've covered the
basics of Pipi and V and we're now ready
to use it to install our first analysis
tool the Jupiter notebook and begin work
doing math and doing data inside of our
browser before we do that I would just
pause for a second and ask are there any
questions about Pippi and V or these
terminal Maneuvers we've been doing
and there's one in that just showed up
in the chat that's probably it happens
to a bunch of folks uh I know it's
happened to me essentially where your
your pip file and your pip block pip
block file uh end up in your main
directory not in the
first python notebook directory
um is there like do you have a
recommended solution for dealing with
that
spec you know I'm guessing a little but
I suspect that happened because people
ran the commands
uh without having changed a directory
into the code directory right so the
picture
is made at whatever location where you
issue the commands right so if you're in
your home directory and you do Pipi and
V install there it's going to create a
new virtual environment there and it's
going to put the PIP file there right
and so
um you could proceed with the class and
work that way there's nothing that would
stop it from working it's just that you
would have sort of all the stuff living
at the root of your computer you know
the reason I made these directories and
moved into them was just to kind of have
a little corner of my computer where
this stuff was happening
um but it wouldn't be necessary so if
you wanted to avoid it I would say uh
look back at uh the the the chapter two
make sure that you make directory the
code and first python notebook
directories and then change into those
directories with CD before you run pit
BNB and if you did that now again I
think you would probably be all right
any other questions
um I'm stuck in my home folder and I'm
trying to move
do I just hit CD code
yes but the code directory has to have
been made right which is what make
directory does it creates the directory
and then you use CD to move into it
after you've done that
the CD code just gives me no such file
directory even though it exists uh then
I'm guessing there's a typo
right so one thing I like to do if I get
confused is open my finder and just look
so like I open my finder here and I look
there's the code directory I know it
exists so you might want to
take a look at your finder make sure
it's there you can type PWD to then kind
of Orient yourself where am I in the
terminal this happens to me all the time
sometimes I think I'm in one place in my
terminal but I'm in another and I get a
little turned around and using PWD LS CD
are the tools to help you kind of sort
that out I think one of our coaches
could probably help you with it if
you're if you're turned around
thanks
okay great we can move on so now we're
going to head into chapter two of the
course which is called hello notebook
and in this chapter we're going to
install the jupyter notebook tool we
discussed earlier which is a
browser-based system for writing
reproducible data analysis
um many newsrooms are using this now and
some are even publishing their notebooks
which have all the code that execute
their data analysis on open source
publishing sites like GitHub so that you
can read and run the analysis yourself
you know for instance you may remember
some of the machine bias series by
propublica
um or um the the
um
the tennis racket by BuzzFeed where they
try to figure out who is throwing tennis
matches using data and all the code that
actually generated those stories is
available in Jupiter notebooks on GitHub
and I have some links here and you can
go and read those and see them yourself
it's not just journals to do this
scientists Scholars uh Wall Street Bros
as discussed and many others uh do this
as well and so but before that you can
write your own Jupiter notebook you have
to install it right because it's just
one of these hunks of python code that's
out there waiting for you so we're
already in at this point our first
python notebook folder which I can
verify by typing PWD which has been okay
I'm there
and so now I'm going to use pit bnv for
real to install something I actually
need and I'm going to install I'm going
to do Pit bnv install
Jupiter lab and the reason it's Jupiter
lab is because that is how it's been
defined
on Pi Pi by the creators of Jupiter who
were at Berkeley and uh the University
of Colorado and Bloomberg and all these
places around the world where there's
these nerds who come together to write
the software they decided to call the
tool Jupiter lab and and put it into Pi
Pi this way and so if that's the term
that we need to use to install it from
Pi Pi so we're going to do pip EnV
install
Jupiter lab and hit enter
now because this is a bigger hunk of
code than yoke 3K and it has to install
more stuff it's just going to take more
time and so we're going to hit this and
it's going to depend on your internet
speed and your computer speed and other
factors but it might take even a minute
or more for this to finish and so I'm
just going to kind of let this chill
and you guys should too and just give
everybody's computer a chance to get
this done
and and I'm going to take this
opportunity need to jump in and tout the
fact that one of the newsrooms that
really publishes a lot of their
notebooks is the LA Times which Ben
didn't didn't go into but
um I actually point my students to the
notebooks that the LA Times Daily desk
publishes all the time it's really
useful uh you walk through that code and
it's just great practice
yeah so here on GitHub is a list of all
of the notebooks we've published here's
one that analyzed uh the the speakers
and Star Wars movies to show sort of the
gender disparity there uh here's where
we scraped Deadspin for some strange
reason I can barely remember here's one
that Iris one of our instructors wrote
that analyzed the rising number of uh of
women being killed in Los Angeles County
in domestic violence episodes
um and they live within GitHub which is
sort of a social network for code so
here is here is the python code that
Iris wrote to do that story
um inside the new The Notebook interface
here's pandas here's Altair right and
we're gonna learn how to do something
quite like this here in a minute to
analyze money in California politics
you can see that mine is still going
locking step often takes a while that's
updating that pitfile lack I was talking
about is what that is
and now it's finished success I love it
I love it when they have like little
colors and emojis and things that make
me feel good
that's how you know it's a newer program
it's been written by millennials
right
and mine is finished
so it might take other folks a little
while to finish so I'm going to give it
a second but what I'm going to do just
to illustrate the point again is I'm
going to run yoke one more time you do
not need to do this I'm just kind of
making a point but if I run that yoke
Dash L again with Pippi and V and it
lists all the install packages look at
that remember there used to just be
three or four things now there's like 20
or 30 things because these are all the
other packages that got installed on our
computer
by Jupiter lab because Jupiter lab is
itself one program but it then calls on
many other programs to do what it does
right because it you know if it wants to
run python code or it wants to have sort
of uh Crypt use cryptography to secure
its website or it wants to send files to
the trash of your computer rather than
write their own tool for doing that it's
going to install other tools that other
people have written on Pi Pi to help
them do what they do right and so
installing Jupiter lab is actually
installing
dozens of other python programs that we
see here right
and you can see they often have really
terrible names like sniffio that's
pretty bad
pickle share how about that one
you know
okay
I'm gonna type uh hold on
I'm going to type clear to clear out my
terminal
Jupiter lab install for everyone
uh no not yet
okay so there's one issue which is you
might be waiting and then this is also
one of those moments where something
could go wrong right like if your Pippi
and V isn't configured correctly or you
have some underlying issue with your
computer this is a moment where it might
like bark at us and say there's a
problem so if somebody if you're not if
if you actually have an error message if
something has gone wrong this would be a
moment to raise your hand and our
coaches can reach out to you and we can
try to figure out what's going on if
you're just waiting we could just wait
another 20 30 seconds and I think
everybody will catch up
foreign
ER lab is installed we're ready to run
it right it's installed inside our
virtual environment so in order to start
it up and get it going on our computer
we need to begin by typing Pippi and V
run just like we did with yoke because
again Pippi and V run is our way of
running something inside of this little
self-contained environment that we've
created right and inside of Pippi and V
run there's a command that actually
basically is the start button for
Jupiter lab this is the command that
says okay I'm ready to spin up the
notebook and start writing code inside
of it and again this is just like an
Arcane thing that was developed by these
nerds and uh you just have to memorize
it or learn it to go and so I learned
this a long time ago from their
documentation so I know that to start it
I need to run the command Jupiter lab
right
um
you know it's Jupiter like the planet
but it's py like python get it guys
some people call it Jupiter which is
actually kind of fun because it's so
nerdy but I think it's meant to be
pronounced Jupiter don't ever call it
you pyter never again I'll never do
anything don't do that none of us should
do that
I don't know I kind of like it
but I want for you for you Derek I won't
all right so it's Pippi and V run which
is saying run it inside the inside the
environment and then the command I want
to run is Jupiter space lab okay I'm
gonna hit enter and that is going to
sort of take over my terminal and like
fire up a little little baby internet
server inside my computer that runs
Jupiter and depending on how your
computer is configured it might even
open a web browser for you automatically
like you can see here on my computer
Firefox just opened up
hooray and here I am inside the Jupiter
lab editing interface right now if your
computer doesn't automatically open a
browser that's okay not a big deal right
what you can do is you can look inside
the terminal
message that's fired up and you can say
to access the server it says either open
this file or open these URLs that are at
the local host or sort of your
computer's position
um and you could just say right click on
that and say open link you could copy
and paste it and paste it into a browser
tab like you know if I say copy and then
I'd paste this into my browser tab we
can see that Jupiter lab is I think
gonna fire up there too
right there it is so I'm going to close
Firefox and keep it in this other one
right and if you've done this you now
have successfully installed Jupiter and
pretty much all the gnarly computer
programming stuff or most of it is
behind us and you're in good shape
very good
okay so I'm going to move that over here
to the left
we have Jupiter lab up and running and
we're now ready to make our first python
notebook right which is the interface
like the one we saw with irises and
there's a launcher right here in the
center that says make a notebook in
python3 and so I'm just going to click
that button
and that's going to make a new python
notebook for here me on my computer and
here is a new blinking Terminal A little
cell of code
where again I'm being asked to do
something right we can see here on the
left there's a file drawer or browser
within jupyter to let you look at your
files so we can see hey there's our pit
file right and there's our pitblock file
and here's a new file which is called
Untitled IPI and B because the I Pi NB
is an IPython notebook which is what
Jupiter used to be called so that's the
file extension
and then the file is Untitled so it's
named Untitled but I could just for fun
you don't have to do this click the
rename button and then I'm going to name
I'm going to name it um G I don't know
what should we call it naming things is
hard I'm going to call Mine Derek right
and so I now have
derek.i pi and B
if I were to go into my file folders go
to mooc go to First python notebook we
can see that there's my file Derek
probably not a good name let me rename
it I'm going to rename it
notebook okay
and you're able to interact with it here
within the browser the same way you
would on the file system
okay now
these cells that we see I'm going to
hide my drawer then by hitting this
little folder button just to give myself
a little more space and I'm going to
pump up the size of this so you guys can
read my code a little better okay now
the way that that notebooks work is
um they allow you to segment the code
that you write into little bite-sized
chunks that are called cells and those
are these little boxes we see just a
single box here on the page with the
blinking cursor that's waiting and
unlike the terminal
these cells are expecting you to write
python code right they're not expecting
us to do LS or PWD or any of those weird
terminal commands they want us to write
python which has its own syntax its own
rules its own system right and so we're
going to start with a very simple piece
of python code which is just two plus
two because when you're writing python
you can take a number you can put a plus
sign between it and guess what it will
add the two things together so I guess
everybody type two plus two and then you
can see above it here
there is a little button that's a play
button like on a vcr and it will execute
the currently selected cell of code
which this little blue thing on the
right indicates so if I click into my
cell write some Python and push play
you'll see that it then prints out
beneath the cell the result of that line
of code right and as I think we all know
two plus two equals four and so now
congratulations if you've never done it
before you have written python code guys
you've done it right your first line of
python two plus two
I see we have a few folks who've raised
their hands and so um our coaches can
maybe help them I'm hoping that this is
broadly worked for everybody though have
I gone too quickly is there any
questions
yeah I uh click two plus two
uh and when I hit play I'm don't get the
result I'm just taking to the next uh
cell and I just noticed that you know
your two your plus is highlighted in
different color mine has not did I not
save something or well it could be that
um your cell is not a code cell so see
how I saw I've selected the cell here
and do you see there's this box here
that says code
there's different types of cells cells
can be code cells or they can be what
are called markdown cells which are the
cells where you write documentation or
you say this line of code is about to do
this and you write little notes and you
put hyperlinks in and you do stuff and
so a notebook is almost always a mixture
of code cells that run code and markdown
cells that document the code right and
so my first guess would be is that your
cell kind of accidentally got turned
into a different type of cell and then
it's not being executed as python code
am I right
yeah I am on code though
um well you could always there's a plus
button here that will insert a new cell
see how I did that look at me add these
cells and there's a cut button that will
remove cells and so if your cells are a
little jacked up I would say just cut
them all out add a new one click into it
make sure it still says code
try two plus two
hit play
that should do it would be my guess
now there's hotkeys for doing all these
things so if I do two plus two and hit
play two plus three it now shows five
two plus four it now shows six but you
know you might get tired of hitting the
play button so you could do if you hit
shift enter it will run it that's a
hotkey that's very hopeful on Jupiter if
you just change there do shift enter and
it re-runs the code right
so that's a you know demonstration cell
not especially useful you know what but
you know so let's get into something
that is still simple but it takes us a
step further so if you're going to have
all these cells which run independently
of each other within your notebook you
need a way to pass information from one
cell to the next cell right so that
you're able to create a chain of things
that are useful and you know the the
fundamental tool for doing that in all
programming languages is the variable
right a variable
is a named sort of thing that stores
information that can be reused in other
pieces of code right and so you save
some information into a variable and
then you do stuff with it right and the
information you save can be numbers they
can be strings of characters they could
be lists of numbers lists of characters
a mixed list of both they can be what
are called dictionaries where there's
like a lookup of a name that keys to a
value there's all sorts of different
data types that can be stored inside
variables depending on what you're
trying to do so let's write our first
variable which will be very simple I'm
just going to call it number right so
I'm just going to type number equals and
then I'm going to say 2.
and then hit the play button and so now
you'll see that nothing got printed out
because the result of the cell wasn't to
print something it was to save the
number two
into a variable called number right and
so if in my next cell I uh just type
number and hit play you'll see that it
prints out too right because this value
has been saved in this cell
right now if I were to make another cell
an hour to do number Plus
three and hit play
see that it comes out as five because
the variable
was added to had three added to it and
then the result was printed out right
and this is just a very rudimentary
example of python within the notebook
now
um the what the this this will seem very
simple at first but what makes the
notebook powerful is you can go back and
change one of the cells let's say I
change two to four right
I re-run that cell and the subsequent
cells and you can see now that number
plus three equals seven and the changes
that I made higher up in the notebook
when everything was rerun rippled down
throughout the code so that the changes
I made sort of flowed down out and
through the system again right
foreign
your Jupiter notebook is really
introducing the python tools that are
going to help you do what you want to do
into the notebook and then writing
rearranging rewriting re-running these
cells to gradually get them to sort of
get where you want to go as part of your
analysis right and the notebook is your
sort of friend and your tool for sort of
doing all that
all right with that we've reached the
end of chapter two hello notebook we're
ready to introduce some of our python
friends to begin looking at how you
would do more sophisticated data
analysis within this environment does
anybody have any questions about the
notebook at this point
I have a python question sure
um is there an
an option to liken JavaScript where
there's a const
to assign a value to a variable that
does not change or is it just kind of
like a quick assignment the way that you
did it here
by default in Python the assignments are
sort of you know editable they're not
permanently saved assignments so you're
once you create a variable you're able
to redefine it you know that's kind of
Python's default behavior and this is
one of the things that can vary slightly
between different computer programming
languages where most languages are
mostly the same in terms of concept but
there are little things about like or
there are sort of fundamental qualities
about languages that can vary and one of
those is whether variables once you
create them are sort of permanently
saved as they're created and the other
is what another is whether a variable
has to be typed or when you create the
variable do you have to say this is an
integer this is a string this is a list
like in a sort of very strict sense
right and python is loose in that way a
python variable once it's created can be
redefined any number of times and it can
really be any type of information
um and that's I think the people who
made python wanted it to be easy and
like kind of fluid and that's why they
did it that way other programming
languages had implemented it in a more
strict fashion right now if you want to
write strict python which sometimes you
do like let's say you're scraping data
and you want it to be very strict about
what you save into the database and if
anything weird comes in the scraper you
want it to throw an error right you know
there are add-ons to python that allow
you to introduce those types of rules to
how the things work but by default they
don't do it
gotcha thank you
[Music]
your your audio was a little warped for
me did anyone hear the question
you could try it in the chat Maybe
okay I see some people reporting some
python errors I think our coaches can
probably reach out and help with you it
probably just has to do with your
Jupiter starting up at some of those
issues of just getting things kind of
booting from your terminal
we're working in our notebook is there
anything that's happening in the
terminal yes so if we reopen our
terminal again underneath the notebook
you can see there's all this
gobbledygook right do you see that on
yours
yes yeah so this is basically when you
started the The Notebook it kind of took
over your terminal so your terminal is
no longer yours it's been kind of
possessed it's been you know it's now
run by Jupiter and the the web server
that is the site is sort of logging out
what it's doing it's just giving you
kind of reports on what's Happening and
you can see that like when I renamed the
file and the file got saved it sort of
logged that to the terminal and I think
it has an automatic save where like
every however many seconds it saves the
file for you as a courtesy and every
time it did that it was kind of logging
what's going on here right
oh
Derek I can see that it says notebook is
not trusted
the notebooks that I created that's not
an issue that's just like a security
feature of the Jupiter notebook that is
trying to like sort of use cryptographic
techniques to sort of like ensure that
there's not a hacker inside your website
like screwing around with it and I think
that those features because the Jupiter
notebooks we're running it on our own
personal computer but they're the
software is actually capable of being
run on a server in the cloud where you
just go to like a private website and
write the notebooks so for instance this
is 100 true if you've worked at Netflix
for instance and you were on the data
science team at the East Hollywood
office or in Los Gatos and your job was
to analyze
um you know how many seconds into the
stand-up comedy special before people
bail you know what I mean or like um to
write machine learning to determine if
you could create a new genre of Chinese
Noir or something you know what I mean
they're using Jupiter notebooks to
analyze the marketing and user data or
or whatever but there's so much data and
their organization is so sophisticated
that people don't install and run the
code on their own computers the Jupiter
notebook is instead hosted in like a
private website that's run by a whole
security team and the data analyst goes
into some private website and they see
100 the same Jupiter like interface that
you're seeing but it's instead hosted
inside this website and in those cases
they might not want to get hacked or
whatever and so there's these features
to sort of secure the The Notebook
but on our private computer it's none of
it's on the web it doesn't matter
make sense
thanks
hey Ben quick question
um was that that when you like ran the
entire notebook again was that the like
fast forward button the like restart
kernel then rerun entire notebook yeah
so
um I didn't quite do that but there are
some useful things that are worth
pointing out that are like that so like
the play button will just run an
individual cell right right but they're
a really common case for us a journalism
is like well I changed something up here
in the notebook and then I want
everything below it to like jam out you
know what I mean based on like the
change and we're going to do that in
class is like there's there's little
tools like in the Run menu you can say
um run all cells and so that'll just do
everything from the top right and you
can do
um restart kernel and run all cells is
sort of like flushing everything and
running it all again because if you run
all the cells let's say you created a
variable but then deleted it and then
renamed it and used it again that's all
kind of like living in the memory of the
computer and sometimes things can kind
of get crossed up and so if you restart
the kernel it's just like flush all the
python and just start over so that
nothing can go wrong right and so if you
if you want to be very you know so
oftentimes when I finish a notebook I'll
do that to make sure there's like
everything still runs after I've like
edited things and deleted things and
goofed around a lot you know
um
but if you worked at a big data science
company you might not want to do that
because cell number six read in 200
million records and if you restart it
you'll have to do that over again you
know yeah yeah
okay thank you so much which is why they
don't have a hotkey for it I'm like in a
fight with them if you go on GitHub on
Jupiter lab I'm like I want a hotkey to
restart and run all the cells and
they're like that's too dangerous we
can't allow it I'm obsessed with the
hotkeys too but I know so you should go
and thumbs up my little feature request
you know
um
and there's a bunch of other things like
that that allow you to cut cells and
paste cells move them up and down uh you
can show little sidebars you can
collapse them there's like a lot of
stuff you can do that's kind of hidden
in these six
okay so for good there we're ready to
move on to chapter three and chapter
three is we're going to begin to write
we're gonna begin to use one of our
python tools to write the code so rather
than just goof around with variables and
numbers we're going to use pandas and
we're going to introduce pandas to our
notebook so that we can
uh begin to take advantage of the many
shortcuts and special features it has
for managing data and and calculating
statistics right and so to do that we
have to go back to our friend Pipi and V
and install pandas because just like
Jupiter lab it's not on our computer by
default right it's something we have to
install and Pippin B is our friend to do
that right now as we pointed out before
our terminal has been taken over right
so if we return to our terminal we see
that Jupiter lab is in here making noise
and if I try to type like PWD and hit
enter nothing happens because I'm no
longer on my terminal and so to get back
to the terminal to run Pippi and V to
install our other tool we have to either
reclaim our terminal from Jupiter lab or
we have to open a second terminal right
that will operate in tandem with this
and either of those methods are okay and
I kind of leave it to you to pursue what
you want but just to illustrate how you
start and stop the Jupiter lab server
I'm going to do it that way myself and
so because it's not immediately apparent
here at my terminal and this will vary a
little depending on your operating
system if I hit control C it will say it
will then prompt me do you want to shut
down this Jupiter server I'll hit Y and
enter
and then it should
um
I waited too long it should then shut
down Jupiter lab and now I've returned
to my terminal where I can type PWD
right however my Jupiter lab is dead the
thing in my browser has now been
terminated and won't run anymore right
so I want to close my browser too and so
if you want to get some practice at this
I would do control C or if you're on an
Apple it might be a command C is that
right guys
okay
thank you and then you just want to say
yes and you want to stop it right so and
um if you're if you feel you're already
advanced and you just want to open a
second terminal window instead that's
fine too but you know this is good
practice I think so Ctrl C we'll close
it down I'm then going to type clear to
clear out my terminal
again I'm going to check where I am with
PWD I'm in first python notebook which
is where my virtual environment is so I
need to be here to do the install right
and now I'm going to install pans with
Pippi and me install canvas
okay and that's going to go again to Pi
Pi it's going to look up pandas in the
phone book it's going to take the code
off the internet download it install it
on my computer and get it ready to go
and pandas is even more complicated than
Jupiter and so it's going to take a
while for this to work right
and it's also possible that after
waiting there's some configuration issue
on your computer with installing pandas
now
one thing that was in our prerequisites
was that on your Apple computer you need
to have xcode installed right and xcode
is the computer programmer add-on to an
Apple computer right and it basically
includes some tools that let the
computer do nerdy things that aren't
worth getting into and it may be
necessary to have xcode installed for
pandas to get on your computer is that
right Andrea
I think so yeah so if you have I could
probably yeah so if you have an error
with compiling the code or something
like that it's likely going to be due to
having not having xcode installed which
is easily done if you're an admin User
it's just an extra step
and uh
and I did we have that documented gosh
we should if we don't
I feel like we may have I may have
overlooked that in my documentation huh
guys
I feel like we used to have it
but I can find that line of code in our
internal LA Times documentation for
folks in case this comes up as an issue
welcome to the LA Times private
documentation site
very exciting stuff
[Music]
we have a little how to set up your
Macbook guide
it just has a bunch of annoying commands
like this because it's just too hard to
do all this crap
and so there is
I believe here
a command that will install xcode
that if anyone has this issue I will
post into our chat
I suspect if you have Homebrew installed
you have xcode installed would be my
guess but
okay
so you can see here on the left in my
terminal that pandas has been
successfully installed
you know if I were to look at my pit
file right which which includes
everything I've tried to install we can
see that it now includes pandas right
because these are the three things that
Ben has used pipnv to install and so
that has been logged in Ben's pitfile
okay that's all done you know if I were
to just again do yolk just for fun you
would see all the underlying
dependencies that get installed as well
and we can see wow we've really
installed a lot of stuff right now on
the computer
there's pandas right there all right
okay again depending on your internet
speed your computer speed this will take
a little longer
um and if you have any errors or buds
that come up just raise your hand and
our coaches can help while we're waiting
does anybody have any questions about uh
pandas or any of this
I would uh Ben I would just say like uh
for folks uh and we'll we'll uh coaches
will be around to get to folks when you
have issues or when you have errors like
that's a super common thing the first
thing you should tell us is not I have
an error but here's my error
um just you know the the specifics will
matter especially when we're doing this
remotely so uh uh so as specific as you
can be that helps us helps us solve and
even just copying and pasting what you
see in your terminal would be a good
start right Derek
yep
okay we'll wait for people to get a
little help there
um
we have pandas installed
and I'm gonna
and that means we're going to move into
chapter three hello panties
we're almost done with all the painful
installment guys this is the last one
for a while
okay
while our coaches are helping let's
discuss how we might get back into our
Jupiter lab environment so that we can
take advantage of pandas uh
oh I have to uh who here in the class
remembers what we need to do to start up
our Jupiter lab and can share it with
the group
was that the hip Envy run Jupiter lab
that's exactly right you got it and so
if we want to restart our Jupiter lab
which we killed a minute ago we have to
use Pippi and V run which can execute a
command inside our virtual environment
and then the command that starts the
Jupiter lab is Jupiter space lab you
nailed it and so to get back into our
Jupiter lab where pandas will now be
available for our use after we've
installed it we need to run this command
another time
okay and so I'm going to hit do Pipi and
B run
Jupiter layup
hit enter same as before
and you can see my Firefox is booted up
but because I want to stick in the same
browser as my other thing which is in
Chrome I'm going to copy and paste the
link into a brave tab
and that will start up for me
you can see here in my case The Notebook
opened right back up where it began
again and again just to kind of make the
point if I were to advance down to
number plus three click on it and hit
play it's going to throw an error and
say look number is not defined does
anybody know why that is
if you haven't rerun your notebook
exactly I haven't rerun The Notebook
even though all the code is still in
here because we killed the Jupiter
server and restarted it it all needs to
be run again from the top right and so
in order for number plus three to work I
need to run all the code above it which
I'm doing with my hotkeys and then voila
it does
so everybody who has their pandas
installed and as jupyter backup should
just try to rerun their cells again
and get it there
I feel like we have a few people who
have uh bugs the coaches are helping
them with so I'm going to stall for a
second and I'm just going to do a little
curlicue on a feature that is not
essential but it's just a useful uh
Jupiter thing that we could spend some
time on you know a minute ago we were
talking about how there's the cells
could be code cells or they could be
markdown cells right so for instance if
we look again at iris's notebook we can
see that when she was finished with it
it wasn't just python code that was all
chained together she also had written
some documentation that explained what
she was up to right so we can say this
is the women homicides analysis by Iris
Lee she has like a summary of her
findings she links to the story and then
throughout the python code you can see
she's created section headings she's
like described what she's doing and
she's done that by mixing in these
markdown cells which is kind of a form
of HTML with the code so into kind of a
little um you know a little white paper
a little thing of Art and we can do that
ourselves by taking one of our cells and
converting what it is so I'm going to
click on my first two plus eight cell
and you see where it says code there I'm
going to pull down that I'm going to hit
markdown and that now you'll see that
the little thing on the left is gone and
the cell looks a little different it's
not formatted if I hit the play button
it literally just says two plus eight
and that's because the notebook is now
interpreting the cell as a markdown cell
or a documentation cell and not python
code and so if I can come in here and I
can start writing like a headline for my
notebook so my notebook is called first
python notebook by Ben Welch right
if I do that and run it
wow it now has like a little bit of text
there right and if I click into it again
and now this is where markdown comes in
markdown has ways of making headlines a
single hash before a line creates a
headline
and so I could say boom hash space first
python notebook play right now I have a
headline you know I've got my little
blog that has my profile page on it so
I'm going to go get that URL that's how
I used to look before kovid
and
I grab that link and then I go in here
and then markdown has a way of making
hyperlinks which you can look up just
how markdown works and you can learn it
you put a little bracket around the text
you do a parenthesis and then you get a
little hyperlink and so now the top of
my notebook has a headline and it has my
name and a little hyperlink and it's by
mixing and matching these coded markdown
cells that you can kind of document what
you're doing
we're not going to get into a lot of
that in class our class is really focus
more on the coding part of it but this
this this markdown feature is just part
of the art of making a sort of nice
notebook
and I find it quite helpful to put like
a little line of text around above
everything I do like you know to find
number variable you know like right
there above what I do and then it's like
you know I could say prince number
variable right and now I can sort of
document what I'm doing as I go for my
own future reference
okay
that was my stalling routine coaches do
we need more time or are we ready to
advance
I'm still stuck we've got a yeah we've
got a couple people who like the the
pandas install just isn't working right
and it's not I'm not clear like there's
two there's two like Avenues here two
types of failures we're getting one is
it just like it the Locking doesn't
complete
uh and then the other one there's a very
specific one that at least a couple
people have run into that is requiring a
[Music]
um
uh what's the way to say this
essentially like it's it's
raising a very specific error uh to
install numpy
uh that references pep 517 that I've
never heard of before but I've Googled
and it seems like it's a real thing but
like the the instructions for getting
out of it aren't have not yet yielded
any success I don't know if you run into
this but that bug I haven't seen now if
your issue is the lock file like the
Locking can take a long time and if your
computer is otherwise taxed with other
things it can take even longer and it
can be very frustrating the lock file
itself is in essential to installing the
tool it's really just about creating the
record in the pipfile.lock which is not
necessary and so if you're having
trouble with the Locking what I would
advise is PIP B and B install pandas and
then dash dash skip Dash lock and that
will install the tool without doing the
lock right which can just lead to it
being more quick and avoiding whatever
your bug you're having for this time so
I'm going to paste that into the chat
and I would say if you're having trouble
with the lock taking forever or crashing
I would say just try it with that
variation for Thing One Thing Two you
sounds like something I haven't heard
before I would bet it it has to do it
might be a 3.9 thing that's just new to
us
um
is there not a way to skip that
verification
it just doesn't complete the install but
it fails that's what that yeah exactly
and do you have xcode installed
yep okay because my first thought was
maybe it was the component that was my
thought too but it doesn't solve so
um that's a new one to me these are on
Apple Computers yep
oh I actually might know this
um so the new Apple M1 chip has been
causing problems with certain open
source software yeah this is actually
isn't an M1 thing this is like a 2017
MacBook Pro
okay then everybody yeah you're right
you're right if you're on a new M1 you
could you could run into this but like
uh but if you're like
uh but yeah it's yeah that's the one
then right there
yeah essentially if you're on Big Sewer
and and M1 in particular you could have
an issue here
and I've for folks who have run into
this I've tried this without you know
without using the the command that says
don't use pep 517 and still no lock
well
this is one I have not seen before the
zoology of bugs has expanded yet again
yeah I I mean I think
like I think like the thing to do is
just not to run this on three nine for
most people like I I like I I my suspect
suspicion is like if we could
essentially like have rolled back the
clock and be like let's all make sure we
start on either three seven or three
eight we probably wouldn't run into this
well
if that is the issue I think the route
to correcting your python version is
using a tool called Pi EnV which is
probably too much to get into in this
class but is a really great python tool
so in the way Pippi and V is a tool that
lets us manage different versions of
python tools Pi EnV is a tool that lets
you manage different versions of python
because over time it as you code more
just using the default installation of
python or trying to change the versions
yourself become such a headache as we're
encountering here that it's useful to
have a tool that will let you install
multiple versions of python and switch
between them which you can see is a tool
that I had installed when I did my which
python it showed that my python is
installed via Pi EnV and I'm able to
jump between Python 3A 373639 depending
on like what's going on in my computer
and I just are on three eight because
that's where I've been for a while and
so I think if you're if you're if you're
stumped by um
by that I think
um ultimately installing Pi e and V
using those techniques and then using it
to switch to say python 3.8 which is the
most kind of common one currently
um and trying it again there is going to
be the route to go I think that's
probably too much for us to cover here
as part of this class and so I think
um we probably need an alternative
installation method for people
um
there is you know
uh I uh there are ways to run Jupiter
notebooks in the cloud without
installing them on your own computer
there's one that's called uh Google
collab if you just Google this real
quick if you wanted to try you could
install a sort of simulation of a
Jupiter notebook that runs inside of
your Google Drive using a tool called
Google collab and it will have pandas
already pre-installed and you could uh
you could try to make a notebook there
and follow along with class using this
sort of cloud Tool uh for the time being
but I think short of that we're going to
need to do the pi NV fixes um which we
just don't have time to do as part of
this class here today I don't think I
would encourage people to Endeavor on it
anyone who is currently stuck at that
stage now in class if after class is
over you need some one-on-one help
getting your computer fixed I would say
you should join
um the first python notebook slack
channel that we've set up on the news
rotary slack and I'd be happy to at a
later date help guide you through trying
to do the pie EnV stuff and getting that
stuff ironed out okay
um collab also comes with Altair
installed by default so
that would be
a way to not have to install anything
else right so Google called
collaboratory is the name of the tool
you could try to jump into that now and
I I bet if you fired that up you'd be
able to catch right up with where we are
in class
okay anything else before we keep moving
with pandas I wonder if we should just
give like a couple minutes for the folks
who want to try to jump into Google
collab because I think there's quite a
few
mm-hmm
I'll do it right now I'm actually still
having an issue
um I think someone else in the chat
wrote this but when I did the Vim uh pip
file I got the this arrow that said
found a swap file by the name Dot
file.swp and it asked me
um it said it already exists and if I
want to open read-only edit anyway
recover quit or abort that does not
matter you could just abort I mean you
know this the swap file is basically
it's it's saving your unsaved progress
it's sort of like backing you up in case
you forgot to save and you want to get
to it later or you want to undo
something and it's really an irrelevant
file
um editing the pit files nothing we need
to do as part of this class I think you
can just abort and move on and you're
fine okay thanks
so I'll go into Google collab here
myself I'll say new notebook right and
Google collab and you'll see that they
have their own
um proprietary spin-off of Jupiter
notebook that they probably hope to make
money off one day uh and in here I can
do number equals two right and I could
do number plus three and I could do all
the same stuff we were doing in the
Jupiter notebook right
and pretty much all the code that we're
about to write will work in here just
fine for the time being I can name my
notebook I hate python 3.9 on OS X oh
sorry Mac OS sorry
and
um
blah blah blah okay
any other questions
and Ben can you do that trick where you
gave yourself a title in the code and
then your author name and yeah totally
we can look at that again real quick
that was just taking one of my cells and
making it into a markdown cell right so
I hit the plus button which will add a
new cell by default it's python that
runs like python right but if I click on
it
select it and then I go to this pull
down menu and I say I would like you to
be a markdown cell instead I can then
start writing markdown woohoo right ah
okay that'll make it uh italic because I
put little things around it and if I do
underscores what will it do
same thing
what is bold two asterisks I can never
remember
yeah bold right
cool
and how did you add the link
it's a it's a little bracket on each
side of the text and then a parenthesis
in the link so this is this is not a
Jupiter notebooks thing this is markdown
so markdown is just like a generic way
of writing kind of HTML ish things
without actually having to write HTML
you can go and read about markdown on
markdown guides and it has all the cheat
sheets for how you do headers and bold
text and ordered lists and black quotes
and all that kind of stuff
I believe you also can just write HTML
right guys you can just do I want a b
tag
and you got to be 10 right or I want an
H2 tag
and I got an H2 tag right
foreign
what was that um News Mercury slack
Channel again you said first called the
news notary slack channel is called uh I
think let me find it I'm going there
right now
it's called fpn
nightcar 21 I think here's the LA time
slack it's uh it's fpn hyphen nikar 21.
and we'll get to the bottom of this bug
uh in that channel once we have some
time to kind of focus on it okay here it
is right here
awesome thanks no problem
foreign
okay I think we're ready to move ahead
now into chapter three hello pandas in
this chapter we're going to import
pandas into our notebook so that we can
begin to take advantage of its many
powerful tools and we're going to get an
introduction to some of the really basic
uh features okay and we're to do it
we're going to use a little sample fake
data set that doesn't have much going on
all right but before I begin in my
notebook I'm going to clear out some of
the stuff I've been doing you don't have
to do it but it's just going to make it
easier for me and you is I'm going to
delete all these cells that I was
goofing around with and you can do that
with the cut feature right here to cut
selected cells or by hitting the X key
and so I'm just going to hit x a bunch
of times maybe hit the cut a couple
times and now I've kind of gotten rid of
all that stuff I can hit the plus key
and now I've got a new empty cell
okay now in my empty cell I'm going to
use a python command we haven't used
before which is called import and import
is the python command for bringing into
your current script one of these
packages that you've installed via Pi Pi
right and so if I type import pandas and
hit plus right it will run the line of
code and nothing will happen that's a
very very good sign right and that means
that my python was able to read in
pandas and now the variable pandas that
has been imported contains all of the
many many many shortcuts and tricks and
tools that Panda has available for us
okay so I would ask everybody to type
import pandas and hit play
foreign if you get an error message it's
because it either hasn't been installed
or something else has gone wrong but if
nothing happens that's very good
now before we continue we're going to
return to that cell and we're going to
make a slight variation to it
we're going to go import pandas space as
space and then PD and we're going to
rerun the cell and what this does is it
does what's called an alias this will
import the pandas library at the shorter
variable name that we put after the ads
and so it's going to be pandas is
effectively renamed as PD this is not a
required thing to do but it's standard
practice in the pandas Community when
you look at examples of pandas code or
pandas documentation you're going to see
that there's this magic variable called
PD which is doing all these different
crazy things right and what it is is
it's an aliased version of pandas the
reason that this is done is because the
creators of pandas even though they
chose the name felt it was too long and
so when they're writing their code
rather than having to write pandas all
the time they would rather just write PD
as an abbreviation and so their standard
practice is when they import the library
to do this Alias it is of course
optional but you know I think it's good
to get in the habit of because it will
help your code be understood by other
pandas programmers and you're just kind
to go in with the flow I personally
think it's sort of a flaw and now pandas
was initially designed but you know what
I can live with it you know and so when
I make a new pandas file I import pandas
as PD okay now
in the next cell this PD variable is now
um able to offer us just a million
different like things to do and you can
access them
excuse me
bye
typing PD
and then if you type a period
um and hit the Tab Key you can see that
Jupiter has a little helper function
that reveals to you all of the many many
many many different features and
functions that the pandas Library offers
including ones we're going to use like
read cxp or read an Excel file right and
so the panda variable followed by a DOT
is sort of your way of then accessing
all of the different things that pandas
can do and so when you're reading files
you're writing files you're converting
files you're doing things you'll often
be typing PD dot whatever it is that you
want to do and learning to use pandas is
learning is learning to know what the
key different features are inside of it
and then taking advantage of them while
there are thousands of them there's
probably only 10 or 15 that we use as
part of any real data analysis and you
don't even really need to know the rest
okay so
we're about to do that in a minute but
before we do that I want to create a
really simple data set that we can use
to do some basic analysis and learn some
of these tricks right and so I want to
create a list of data that is just some
numbers that we can analyze right and
I'm going to do that by making a new
variable called my underscore list
equals right and then I'm going to do
two flat brackets and this is your way
in Python of saving a variable and
storing within that variable a list of
of things and inside my list I'm going
to do
a few even numbers 2 4 6 and 8 right and
then I'm going to hit the play button
and so I now have saved into my variable
a list with four numbers in it two four
six and eight right and if you were a
skilled python programmer you could do
all kinds of stuff with this you could
Loop through it you could multiply them
all you could sum them together you
could do all kinds of stuff but you
would need to know quite a bit of python
to do that navigation and what makes
pain is good is it has shortcuts that
makes doing that kind of stuff easier
right but in order for your list to take
advantage of them you have to sort of
feed your datas to pandas you have to
say pandas here's my data I want you to
to like level it up and make it easier
to work with right and so inside the
world of pandas the sort of like super
list the list that's able to do a lot of
cool things is called a series that's
what they decided to name it and so in
order to take advantage of it we need to
convert our python list into a panda
series which we're going to do in our
next cell right and so I'm going to name
I'm going to create a variable to start
it's my series my underscore series
equals right and then here's where I'm
going to hit that PD so PD is the little
pandas tool belt Dot and then it's
capital S Series right so this is the
pandas series maker it's the thing that
can create a new series for you
I'm going to open a parenthesis
which is going to sort of feed
information into the series and then I'm
going to pass into it my underscore list
and I'm going to hit play and so what
we've done here is we've taken our
previous variable my list we've sort of
fed it into a pandas series
and then we've saved that series as this
variable called my Series right and then
I've hit the play button to run it
nothing happened very good
now once we have a series we can
immediately do all kinds of cool Panda
stuff including running a lot of
different descriptive statistics right
and so I can do so my series the
variable it now has its own little Dot
and magic things it can do and so if I
do my DOT series sum open parenthesis
close parenthesis and hit play it will
sum all the numbers in the series and
print out the results right so these
four numbers two four six and eight
added together are 20 right and that
worked for four numbers in this case but
it would also work for four million
numbers right or whatever database of
information you were to pass in right
which we'll get to later with real data
right
there's a bunch of other you know we all
know this descriptive statistics right
my series dot Max open paren close print
to execute that we'll then return the
maximum number in the list which is
eight right my underscore series dot Min
open paren close paren play we'll return
the minimum number in the list right
what's another descriptive statistic I
bet somebody knows one
median the median yes and like
calculating a median is kind of
complicated right and like and like uh
and you might in writing python code to
do that's a real hassle but in pandas if
you just do my series dot median open
paren close paren it'll return the
median number which using the default
median maker there's different
strategies for this it took the split
the difference between these guys right
and it returned five
right the average is another one like
that right in that case it's called a
mean in pandas is what they chose to
call it
right
and then uh another descriptive
statistic is of course the standard
deviation and unfortunately they chose
to call that the STD and so you do STD
open paren close paren and it'll return
the standard deviation and so on right
um if you were to uh do the dot and then
hit it and then hit hit the tab key
right afterwards you could see you could
then preview
uh all of the many different things that
a series can do right so Series has a
lot of different things you can do
kurtosis
right uh and all of these are documented
inside the pandas documentation if we
were to say Google pandas series Max for
instance we would find that there's a
page here in the pandas documentation
that explains to you how that Max
feature works right and it links to some
other ones you might want to do like
there's some
Etc and you can kind of go through this
documentation and you can learn kind of
all the different things a series can do
right here's pow
which is going to do an exponential
power of the series right and stuff like
that there's a lot of different
mathematical things that can be done
but these basic ones I think are ones we
use a lot in journalism what's the sum
what's the max what's the Min what's the
central tendency right
and then there's kind of the helper
function that I kind of like called
describe
my series dot describe open parenthesis
close parenthesis run it and it actually
prints out a bunch of them it gives you
the count the mean the deviation it
gives you a couple different cut points
on the percentile including the median
which of course is the 50th percentile
right and you can kind of see all of
them like at once and that's like a
quick way to get a look at your column
of data to like see what it says
um any questions about these kind of
basic series tools
um I have a question yeah when I ran my
series
um it gives me a vertical list of odd
numbers and even numbers and the D type
just I'm assuming it by describing it as
ink 64. yes so this is an array of four
numbers that we're passing through and
I'm wondering does that generally happen
it just fills in the gaps oh no this is
just it's a coincidence so okay so so
what you've done if I understand it
right is you've printed your series out
as I've just done here is that right
yeah is it just numbering the it's it's
saying what index each number is that
okay exactly so this is a panda this is
a panda's feature we haven't talked
about which is every row is indexed
with a sort of incrementer by default
right so Row one is zero in computer
programming they often start counting
with zero for some reason and so this is
just the unique sort of num you know um
incrementer of it within the series
right and then these are the values
um as you get more advanced you can set
the index yourself like let's say you
have a unique identifier for instance or
you want to group a a hierarchical index
there's all these fancy ways to do that
stuff but we won't get into that in
class the index you can do pretty much
everything you want to do in pandas
without even knowing the index exists
but there are cool things you also can
do with it
okay thanks
and the data type is is an integer you
know data type
um one reason why pandas is fast and
people like it is it doesn't use the
default python data types it uses these
underlying custom numpy data types which
just more quickly process data and they
have sort of strange names like in 64.
other questions about the series
okay so to illustrate kind of the the
some of the earlier points about the
notebook itself and how it can be useful
I'm going to go up here and I'm going to
change these numbers right I'm going to
do 1 5 10
106. just some numbers I made up right
and then I'm going to go to the top I'm
gonna hit run and I'm going to say run
all cells and everything will run again
from the top right but you can see that
the result of all the functions has
changed and updated to say the new sum
is 155 the new Max is 106 right and we
were able to just really quickly repeat
all of our work by by changing one cell
and then hitting a single button to
rerun it all right and as you iterate
and work quickly and fudge around with
numbers this is just really really
useful because you know um and it's and
it's also
um a way in which what you do is
reproducible you know if you were to do
this kind of thing in Excel and write a
bunch of custom pivot tables or little
functions you might have to go back and
do all the clicking and remember the
order of how you did anything to like
reproduce the work but because you've
done it in this way you can make a
change kind of Upstream in the
information and it will all flow
Downstream again when you rerun it
um and then imagine that your data
stream coming in is live on the internet
and updates daily right you'll be able
to just flow it through every single day
kind of in this automated way without
having to click click click click click
the same 10 things every day you know
which we'll get to with the real example
here in a minute
other questions about the series or
pandas before we get into some real data
okay great so we're going to move on to
chapter four uh hello money in politics
this is just kind of um there's this
more written here than we need to say
for this class but um you know part of
the mission of this curriculum initially
was to educate journalists here in
California about how California's
campaign Finance system works and so
here you can find some information about
uh Cal access which is California's
database of money and state house
politics this is the money that goes
towards races for the Governor State
House races for State Assembly and State
Senate and crucially here in the state
of California are many many many many
many many ballot measures as you may
know California is famous for loving to
put yes or no questions on the ballot
which are often uh irrelevant or
rip-offs but are occasionally incredibly
high stakes and very very important uh
famous ones in the past have included
um
uh Banning gay marriage in the in the
one we're about to study legalizing
marijuana uh this last election cycle we
had a very important and controversial
one about the employment status of gig
workers
um and every now and then some really
important stuff kind of goes through
this and all of the money that goes into
it flows through this database called
Cal access which which was actually
created as a result of a ballot measure
itself uh in the 1970s and um it has a
kind of an accounting system where the
Committees that are formed to raise and
spend money to Advocate yes or no in
these ballot measures have to have sort
of transparent bank accounts where they
post into this government database the
amount of money they've raised who their
contributors are the amount of money
they've spent what they've spent it on
whether they support or oppose the
measure and then that database becomes
kind of our really only public record of
the money that's flowing into the system
and in the case of some of these high
stake measures like ones that have to do
with regulating Pharmaceuticals or
genetically modified food corporations
can arrive and spend hundreds of
millions of dollars to try to influence
the outcome of the of the measure in
fact the the gate worker measure last
year uh Uber and other companies spent
some much money it shattered the record
for the costliest ballot measured in
California history with hundreds of
millions of dollars uh spent for and
against
um and so if you're a reporter in
California this database is a way to try
to cover what's happening with that
money now there are databases like this
I think in all 50 states there can
correct me where each state has passed
its own version of campaign Finance
regulation usually these laws followed
the Watergate scandal in the 70s and
what's resulted is this sort of
fragmented system where each state has
its own sort of variation on a database
like this and on regulations like this
that result in sort of the government
puking out sort of gnarly data that you
can try to like fiddle through to find
and tell stories right and so did I get
that right
yeah and it's fantastic it's just as
great as it sounds
yeah and um
and so in this course we're going to get
into we're going to use some some data
that I have sort of curated out of the
gnarly database to avoid some of the
nastier stuff you have to do to work
with it
um and we're going to have two files
that we read into from the calexis
system that are about the ballot
measures in November 2016 when there
were 17 on the ballot and there was a
whole set of committees that were
organized both for and against those 17
measures and then each of those
committees reported lists of
contributors people who gave them money
to support their campaign and for them
to spend and so the two data files that
we're going to read into pandas next for
our real work now are going to be a list
of all the Committees from November 2016
and a list of all the contributors to
those committees right and that is going
to come up next in uh chapter
um five hello data okay and this is
where we're going to use pandas to read
in that data before we do that does
anybody have any questions about
campaign Finance or the California
system or any of the above
um we have some people on this call not
me who have uh Decades of experience
with this and so this is anything you
want to know that you could probably get
an answer
foreign
out the federal system is in fact
entirely different as well for
presidential and for congress that's its
own Federal tracking system
no okay well it is campaign Finance
um so before we begin again I'm going to
clear out my notebook of some of my
cruft you don't have to do this you
could just keep writing but I just don't
want to distract people and so I'm going
to use the X key to clear out everything
except import pandas right so I back
down to import pandas I'm going to hit
plus to make a new cell and now I'm
ready to go
okay at the top of chapter five hello
data we have a table that has two
hyperlinks and these hyperlinks go to
the two data files I just talked about
one all of the committees or the quote
bank accounts that are raising money
right and the other the contributions
these are the individual checks that
people wrote to these committees that
had to be disclosed according to the
campaign Finance law right and what
we're going to do is we're going to use
pandas to read those files into our
notebook so we can begin to manipulate
them right and the tool that does that
is called read CSV and so I'm going to
go right down to this section called
creating a data frame and I'm going to
copy this whole line of code which is
long because it has a long URL
and I'm going to paste it into my cell
and I'm going to hit play
and what we can see if we look at it is
we're calling in that PD Alias like the
tool belt right of all the pandas tools
and we're taking advantage of a function
that's inside there called read CSV does
anyone on the call know what a CSV is it
could define the acronym for others
comma separated values oh beautiful and
what are those
it's a type of data set in order where
um the machine reads like each comma as
a new cell
is that correct exactly exactly and it's
sort of a neutral flat way of storing a
spreadsheet of data and so here in my
web browser tab you can see the CSV or
comma separated values that is the list
of committees and it's really just a
gnarly term for a spreadsheet and we can
see that the first row is all the header
rows of the spreadsheet which are each
separated
by a comma right and then below that is
each row of the spreadsheet where each
value is then also separated by a comma
right and so
what we're doing with pandas read CSV is
we're giving it the URL to this file
which pandas is then reading in and
parsing as a spreadsheet
and this is effectively the pandas or
python version of opening up a
spreadsheet in Excel or another
spreadsheet program right you're having
the computer program read in the data
and parse it into a table of rows and
columns right and what pandas calls that
spreadsheet is a data frame a data frame
is a kind of generic computer
programming tool for a table of columns
and rows or a spreadsheet that has a lot
of like fancy special properties that
you can use a data frame can be filtered
it can be sorted it can be grouped it
can be aggregated and so all the things
that you do in an Excel spreadsheet with
sorting filtering pivoting right you
could do with a data frame and you can
actually do quite a bit more and that
generic data for interim isn't exclusive
to pandas it's also used in R to
describe how you read in a table of data
into our statistical software too and
probably other programs that I'm
unfamiliar with and so what you're doing
when you're reading it in is you're
reading in a data frame which is
effectively a collection of those series
that we were looking at before with each
column in the table being a pandas
series
okay and you can see that by running the
code it just puked out the result of the
table here into
my browser and if I widen my window we
take a look at it we can see at the end
of the day it's just a spreadsheet right
here are the columns here's one called
the prop ID this is the unique
identifier of the proposition remember
there's 17 propositions that year
's the Cal access prop ID this is the ID
of that proposition inside the state
database Cal axis right here's another
idea that ID that our team created
here's the name of the proposition right
proposition 51 School bonds proposition
52 State fees proposition 67 referendum
blah blah blah right
so here on the left part of the table we
see we have all the columns that
describe the proposition that this
committee was formed to advocate for or
against and so because there are
multiple committees for each proposition
you can see that the propositions repeat
because we have one row per committee
the proposition information is on the
left hand side
if I scroll to the right
we can see that the committee
information is on the right hand side
there's a unique identifier for the
committee and you can see that the
committee's names are here and these are
these hilarious euphemistic names that
you see at the bottom of television
commercials you know save the bag ban
yes on 67. you know yes I'm 51
Californians for Quality dog food or
like whatever right and so those funny
names that you see in the television
commercials oftentimes correspond to the
Committees and bank accounts that you
see in this data and the regulations
that require them to be disclosed on the
commercials right are connected to the
regulations about these committees and
so the Committees oftentimes have the
goofy names because that's what allows
them to do it on TV ads right those two
things are directly connected and then
you can see we have a final column
that's crucial that for each committee
they have to file and it is recorded
whether they support or oppose the
ballot measure that they're advocating
on so are they four
legalizing recreational marijuana or are
they against it right that will be
logged in here are they four Banning gay
marriage are they against it Etc support
or a post so yes on 51 of course
supports proposition 51. and this is our
first data set all right
now
you can see that the result was just
puked out into the the console here in
the notebook and it's not going to be
reusable in future cells and that's
because we didn't save the result of the
read CSV function into a variable and so
if we want to take this data frame and
we want to do stuff with it as we go
along right we need to save it into a
variable the same way we saved the
number earlier on right and so what I'm
going to do and there's an example here
you can copy and paste is I'm just going
to save it into a variable that I call
committee underscore list and I'm going
to rerun the code
and so now the result of this function
which is that data frame of data has
been saved to the committee list
variable okay and it's going to be
available for us to use in our
subsequent cells right
now just like the series had all those
fun functions like Som and Min and Max
right the data frame has its own set of
fun functions let's cover a couple of
those really quick there's two that
people use all the time right and you
access them by typing your variable
again I'm going to copy and paste it
because that's the professional lazy way
to do it committee underscore list dot
h-e-a-d head open parenthesis close
parenthesis and play will print the
first five rows of your data set and
this is just a common technique to kind
of take a peek you know what I mean hey
what's inside my data right by typing
committee dot list underscore head I can
take a little peek
I could even substitute in different
numbers like if I put the number one
it'll just show the first record if I
put the number 10 it'll show the first
10 records right and so anytime you have
a data frame this head command is a
helpful way to just get a look at it and
kind of see well what are in my columns
and rows exactly right
the second the second kind of common
command for inspecting a data frame is
called info
if I type committee
underscore list dot info open and close
parenthesis it will print out this which
is a little report card about the
columns or Series in my data set and so
it says to me here Ben you have 102 rows
in your data set you have these eight
columns which we were looking at earlier
here's the names of the columns right
here's the data type of what we think is
in those columns so the ones that thinks
are numbers are integers the ones that
it thinks are like strings or text are
called objects and pandas that's what
it's called is not a good reason for
that that's just what they call it and
so when you have an object column that
means it's words it's letters it's text
when you have an integer column that
means it's a number which means you can
sum it and add it and things like that
and so this is a nice way to get a look
at your table we can see we have 102
rows we have these columns they're these
data types and here it'll even tell you
if you have any empty cell for any null
values this will give you a report card
there and so I can see that I have 102
rows and every one of my columns has 102
things so I have no empty cells in my
data everything's filled in
okay
um okay so as far as reading in your
data frame and doing this basic
inspection with head and info are there
any questions
no okay so before we begin
or before or the next thing to do
is to read in our other data table right
so we have this data table which is our
committees and then we have our second
David data table which is all of the
contributions or all of the checks that
were written to these committees right
which are disclosed by a form that has
to be filed with the state regulator and
I have another read CSV
uh line of code that I'm going to copy
and paste out of the documentation and
this one will read that second
spreadsheet into another data frame and
this data frame is called contrib list
contrib being an abbreviation for
contribution
right
so you can see that that takes a little
while to run and then because the number
appears here on the left that means it
finished hooray
who now if I want to get a look at the
first few rows of the data frame what do
I type somebody tell me
untrib underscore list uh period head
current yep and then open parenthesis
close parenthesis
you got it and just like in the terminal
there's autocomplete if I type contrib
and hit tab it will fill in the rest of
the variable for me very nice
and now we get a peek at the first five
rows of our contributes there's a couple
things about this table I want to point
out and how it works but we can see that
it has a different set of columns than
our contributions list but some of them
are shared we can see here on the left
hand side of this table that there is an
identifier called the Cal access
committee ID this is the unique
identifier of the committee that
received the check right and you can see
that their name is right next to it so
here the first one is adult use campaign
for proposition 64. right I think that's
actually our proposition about marijuana
so this committee which has this ID
is reporting this check right and you
can see here's all the information about
the person who wrote the check and
there's quite a bit in here more than
many people may realize
Gretchen Bergman of Spring Valley
California right on September 18 2016
right
wrote a check to that committee for over
here on the right hand side there's a
column called amount for 84 dollars
right and her she listed on her form
disclosing this check that her employer
was a company called A New Path
and that her job was as the executive
director right and so this is one of the
the checks that went to this committee
and each one of these rows is a similar
check each one has the name of the
contributor it has their location it has
some information about their line of
work and it has the amount of money that
they gave right and
um this type of thing is where the data
like this is where every campaign
Finance story about donors you've ever
read came from right journalists like
the ones on this call
work with lists like this to try to
identify the top donors the top
industries
Etc to figure out and describe what's
going on with our political campaigns
here and you know the data is you want
you you know you probably won't be
surprised to learn pretty imperfect
people are really able to put whatever
they want into the employer and
occupation field uh people
inconsistently spell their names they
give different answers to these
questions over time there's no unique
identifier for a donor over time at all
and so aggregating up who's given the
most money requires cleaning up
variations making decisions about who to
combine that gets more complicated when
you get into things like husbands and
wives decide figuring out how much money
the oil industry is given requires
looking at things like the occupation
and employer field and choosing to
categorize those things
um based on what you read there which
can also change over time as companies
change over time and there's a very sort
of messy imperfect process that goes
into refining data like this into the
the stories that we tell in this case
our goal is to figure out in the case of
uh the marijuana legalization measure
which side supporter oppose raised more
money and who were the top contributors
to each side right and so what we're
going to do in the subsequent chapters
of this this class is we're going to
merge these two data sets together we're
going to filter down to the ones that
were just limited to the single ballot
measure that we're interested in and
then we're going to begin to write
analytical code that groups and ranks
and sorts the data to ask and answer
those types of questions that I was just
articulating right and the two data sets
are going to be able to be fused
together to achieve this using their
common identifiers and by merging the
tables right because we have the
identifier of the committee and the
contribs file we can merge it to the
Committees file and we can do what we
need to do to kind of make this work and
that process of wrestling with this data
and then learning five or six core
analytical techniques like filtering
sorting ranking merging Etc and then
chart making is what the remainder of
the class is going to be and at this
point I'm going to hand it off to my
colleague Iris Lee who's going to pick
it up where we are now and teach you how
to use pandas for real to actually do
this journalistic uh investigation that
we're on okay this might be a good
minute to just also give Iris a minute
to take over the the screen and pick up
where I've left off and also to answer
any questions that we have from people
in the crowd does anybody have any
questions yeah um Ben uh I'm a little
bit of a campaign Finance junkie I'm
just curious if anybody has taken the
time to build this database or something
like this for local uh for like uh local
and County races um or that is something
that hasn't been done yet
you know you you
um you point out a hole in my
description of the system right we have
the federal campaign Finance system
which which tracks the money in
presidential and Congressional races we
have these State systems which track
them at the State House level right in
the Statewide level but then there is a
third layer yet below that for local
races for races for the mayor of your
city or for your board of County
Supervisors or your sheriff or your
district attorney all of those
um are are collected and tracked in the
hodgepodge of systems that are set up by
city and county governments Across
America and there's no one system for
that and it really varies a lot from
place to place you know and so there's
not one database there are places that
have tried to aggregate it I don't think
anyone's done it with much success and
the problem is is they're just these
fragmented different broken screwed up
systems and it's just a gigantic effort
to do it
um the fundamentals of how to like
understand the data is kind of the same
because the regulations are all very
similar things like contribution caps
committees some stuff we're going to get
into a minute about dealing with how
things are itemized those are similar
but your data source and the structure
of the source data is going to vary from
place to place you know uh in in Los
Angeles County
um you know which is home to 10 million
people and it's the largest most
populous and in some ways one of the
wealthiest places in the world you know
the largest most populous County
incredibly wealthy place
um supposedly liberal and advanced our
County Board of Supervisors five people
who rule over 10 million still report
all the money in their races on paper
and it's not digitized and they have and
based on a series of stories that my
colleagues like Malloy Moore have done
they pay people to key punch them into
an electronic system after they're filed
by paper and then they don't appear
online until days or weeks after it's
actually important to look at them
and and I'll just add that like I think
I think my the student
the student story on this that
La published more than half of
California's counties don't even have
that they can't local campaign Finance
on online at all and that includes Los
Angeles County which is just shocking
yeah
great um
and so it's it's it's pretty bad out
there
um I I personally think that getting
into your local races is a great way to
is a great way to cover what's up in
your city in a way that a lot of other
reporters aren't and you don't have to
totally Master it but learning a lot of
the tricks like we're covering here
today is going to let you
um do that so I I don't want to give any
spoilers but by the end of this class we
will have discovered a lead to a story
that nobody covered at the time in the
state of California about the one of the
top donors
they've been just a mechanical thing you
started with the simple list of numbers
and I guess at some point it became a
matrix that's right that's that's the
that's exactly right that's the
difference between the series and the
data frame right so the series is the
pandas jargon or terminology for the
column of data for a single column right
like a list of all the amounts right or
all the committee names and then the
data frame is the table or Matrix right
which is it's a spreadsheet right it's a
list it's a group of columns right
um and that happened when we did the
read CSV function
because the read CSV function read in a
spreadsheet of data that we had prepared
which was then converted into this data
frame
got it and it just sort of knows what's
the rule and what's the column by the
way it's read in exactly because of the
comma separated value data format which
is the common generic format of
spreadsheets
and so if you opened it in Excel Excel
would have parsed it the same way
thanks excuse me all the columns should
be of um made of one type I mean the old
uh
for example one column all record is the
strings or another column all later is a
a numeric the right
uh they could be so really the data type
of each series can vary right there's
not like a um a rule or law but what
pandasbus by default is it sort of it it
guesses so pandas when I did read CSV
behind the scenes without me knowing
about it it did what's called sniffing
the data it read the first 100 rows or
so it sampled the data it looked at what
was in there and then pandas made a
decision and it said this column is an
integer this column is a string etc etc
right I think yes now sometimes it guess
is wrong and so
so there's a when you when you do read
CSV there's an option called D type and
you can specify I want this column to be
a string or this column to be an integer
and you can force it to the data type
that you prefer right thanks thanks yeah
the most common example of this is of
course fips codes fips codes are the
identifiers for States and counties in
the United States and they have leading
zeros so the state of California's
unique identifier is zero six and pandas
will strip the leading zero and make it
an integer and then I have six and then
it can't join to another data set I pull
my hair out you know and so I have to
always tell pandas no the fips code is a
string it's not an integer right thank
you I completely understand thank you
yes
zip codes are also
a pitfall
especially if you're in Vermont where
every zip code starts with a zero right
I bet that's
oh my God
so you have to write all this code to
like put zeros on the front of
government zip codes I bet sometimes
like insert the zero back in excuse of
like string padding function but you
have to remember to do that otherwise
you're gonna regret it down the road yep
other questions yeah
um quick question so I'm kind of a
self-professed um our user but I'm
really interested in trying to you know
get up on python um and I noticed
um like the way that R handles um
different data types in a specific
column is it will just like have a list
in in like what what R's equivalent of a
list is in that column does python or
pandas I should say specifically have a
way that it handles like different data
types being in the same column so if
they were mixed data types like it was
like hodgepodge
um Iris can maybe correct in here but I
think it just says it's an object right
and then you kind of have to figure it
out object will say Tech would be
usually string but it can be a mixed
data type like a list and that that can
be frustrating yeah interesting yeah
there's many things that I think pandas
can improve at I would say that's one
thing right there
um I when we're working on something
that's like serious like you know our
coronavirus tracker or something I'm
uptight about I will explicitly declare
the data types even though it's right
code because I just want to be sure you
know yeah plus for errors and stuff like
yeah it's just probably better be more
explicit but okay that's an interesting
thank you it also will run faster the
sniffing of the data set can actually
slow down the computer especially when
the data set is very large and so if
you're reading in a large data set
declaring the data types as a way to
make it go quicker
foreign
okay any other questions before I hand
it off to Iris
is there um a method for a non-csv data
types oh yes there are many many methods
um so like if I do PD dot then I do read
underscore and I hit tab it will show
them all right so you can see the pandas
can read an Excel file which is super
handy right it can also read an Excel
file from a URL so you can like just
scrape government spreadsheets right off
the internet right it can read a fixed
width format file if you're like a 90s
baby like me
um it can read HTML tables it can read
Json format which is really common and
it can read SQL databases you can
actually write SQL code in your pandas
which is pretty cool or you can read in
a whole table directly there's a bunch
of stuff like that
thanks
[Music]
anything else
I just was curious can
can python
manage the data or would you do that in
like your XLT or your wherever the data
is coming from like if you wanted to
change the data that you were at oh you
could definitely change and edit the
data here in pandas pandas has a lot of
techniques for like selecting a row and
editing it or one thing iris is going to
show you how to do is how to compute a
new column I think we'll get to that at
some point where you want to like take a
couple columns and like make a new one
based on what's in there
um and then there's functions for
writing files out to different formats
too so we could read it in as a CSV and
we could write it out as an Excel file
if we wanted to for instance or out as a
Json file or whatever else
but yeah the the there's there's all
kinds of stuff like that
okay I think with that I'm going to hand
it off to Iris Lee I'm going to stop
sharing my screen so that she can share
hers I'm going to stay on and mute and
be coaching uh as she picks up I think
with what chapter six Iris
yep chapter six okay
hi everyone my name is Iris Lee can you
guys see my screen
yes okay cool
um all right so we're going to start at
chapter six
if you're using collab by the way I
really have to show you this
um if you're on Google collab there's
this phone there's this uh thing on
tools that settings and if you go to
miscellaneous you could
get your notebook in Corgi or Kitty mode
and then it'll have these little corgis
running around on top I just love it so
much
um and you'll see some kitties too
coming around so if you're in collab
feel free but anyways
um so let's start where we left off so
we looked at two data frames the
committee's list and also the contrib
list and from this point on we're going
to explore the committee list data frame
first
okay so I'm just going to start a cell
on the bottom
um
and just start from the top
so sometimes when I'm looking at like
two data frames like I am now I kind of
forget all the column names right it's
like really easy to forget
um so what I like to do is kind of like
what Ben showed you the head method but
I just kind of like to print out just
the first line
and if you want to just do that you
could just put one between the
parentheses on their head and then you
can kind of see like the very first line
of your data frame so sometimes I'll
just put this up top here so that I know
what the column names are and I know
what to type
so we're going to look at this column
called prop name
to select a column in a data frame it's
pretty straightforward all you have to
do is type the data frame's name which
is committee list at this point
and put a dot and put the column's name
and we do that by saying prop name
and now you can see this is kind of like
the series object that Ben showed you
where things are indexed on the left
side but you can see all the prop names
in this data frame and there's 100 to
not different but hundred two lines
the same line as the data frame right
at times when you use different kinds of
data sets sometimes the column names are
not clean like this sometimes column
names may have spaces or capitalization
and one way and if it does have spaces
in between this dot method will not work
in pandas so what you have to do is you
have to do like a bracket and a
quotation and then put the column name
and it's exactly the same thing
so let's say this prop name had like a
space in between that this is like the
notation I would use
but because it doesn't I can kind of do
this like real quick shortcut of prop
underscore name
and then here um I'm not pressing play
I'm Just Doing shift enter just to run
the cell real quickly
so here um
we see a list of prop names there was
like some props propositions that has to
do with school bonds referendum to
overturn ban on I don't know what that
is something about hospitals but we are
going to
try to look at what kind of prop names
are here and how many are there so kind
of like the frequency of how often does
this proposition 51 come up in this
whole data frame okay and in order to do
that we are going to select the column
that we want to explore by typing the
same thing committee
list prop name
and we're going to do this method called
value count
open and close prints
and this value counts is like a method
that you use on the series kind of like
a sum or mean but it lets you see how
many times each type
comes up so let me just expand the
screen so it's a little cleaner
so as you can see that there is at least
13 rows that mention proposition 57
there's like 12 of proposition
proposition 56 and all the types all the
frequencies that this proposition name
comes up in this data frame
um so
we
are going to all right
so sometimes this in this like series
would you mind bumping up your fear of
font size here oh yeah a little just
like control plus I do it
okay
there you go is that better folks a
little better
okay great
um
so now um we're seeing the value count
of each prop name but this is in this
like series format very texty kind of
hard to read so what we can do here is
we could do a reset index
so I'll just type
the same thing copy and paste and then
right reset
index
and pandas indexes it back into a data
frame
so now you can see kind of in this like
clean tabular format how many times each
proposition name comes up
anything to add
coaches no uh one particular question
and do we always need apparentice after
a value count or is it okay to cut out
um yeah what's the difference
that's a good question I've never done
it without parentheses then do you have
an answer for this
you definitely need to do it it wasn't
counting if you did it before you'll see
oh yeah it was a list of 102. I don't
know why that even returns anything I
think yeah
this is I think this is just a a quirk
of how python prints stuff out because
it's it's printing out the function as a
bound method and then just the whole
series following it it's like printing
two things
I see yeah so yes probably the string
representation of the series if you want
to get into it
okay
all right
cool
so we're going to the next chapter
filters
so the specific proposition that we're
looking at that today is the proposition
64 which asked if marijuana should be
elite legal or illegal in California
um as you guys all know it's legal in
California so it did pass but
um we're going to filter this data frame
to kind of just look at the Committees
that supported or opposed this specific
proposition and in order to do that we
will have to filter this data frame
um not this data frame but the
committee's list data frame and just get
the rows that mention this proposition
64. the marijuana legalization
initiative
so in order to do that we'll do a
filtering method and one way to do that
is to use an operator like double equals
greater or smaller this is kind of
similar to
um in SQL like where function so double
equals in functions mean that
it's not like setting a variable but
it's it's like asking a question is this
on the left side the right side so if I
do one is one then it's true so it
returns are true so we're going to do
this like similar method to filter this
data frame
so
one so first I'm going to set a variable
that is the prop name that I want to
filter on so I'm going to call it my
prop
and I'm going to set it as this prop 64
which on your
notebook there should be
um
you can like copy and paste and I'd
rather do that because I'm not very good
at typing
so I'll just copy and paste
and I'll just and now the my prop
variable is
set as this proposition legalization
initiative statue so if you print out my
prop
it is what I said it as and I'm kind of
doing this so that I don't have to type
this whole thing over and over again
which will like introduce errors
um and in order to filter the data frame
on this specific prop I will name the
data frame again which is committee's
list
and then we're going to put square
brackets
and we're going to call the column and
we all know the column is called
committee
list
dot prop
name right
and I'm going to filter it to the rows
of the data frame where the committee
list prop name is equal to this my
prompt
right so I'm going to a double equal
sign say my prop
so what this does is this filters the
whole data frame that has all these
different propositions in them but only
targets the ones that have proposition
64. so as you can see this new data
frame that we created from this filter
has
13 rows or 11 rows because they were 11
times this showed up in the whole data
frame and they're all proposition 64.
and now we're going to name this into a
new variable
and I'm going to call it my
um
my committees okay
is it my committees yes okay cool
so I like to think of variables as like
these like little jars that you put like
labels on so now that I've like filtered
this done this like whole filter I'm
gonna just name it my committee so that
I don't have to do this over and over
again and I know that I just have to
just pull out this my committees in
order to use what I've filtered from the
Committees list
and now we can again kind of do the same
thing that we did with the other two
data frames and run the head and the
info method to see what's in there my
committees
we can look at the first five lines
or we we can also look at info
and now you see this data frame unlike
the other one it has only 11 11 rows but
because we've only pulled out the
proposition 64.
um
prop names
okay
but it keeps the same columns
good
okay
all right moving on any questions
I'm filtering
no okay
so now that we have filtered down to
this contribute
oh so our next job is to filter down the
contributors list the contributors who
have
spent money to support or oppose this
particular
proposition so we're going to go back to
our contrib list
and we're going to merge the contriblist
file into my committees so if you guys
go up
your notebook if you look at your
contribute list you'll notice that we
Ben had mentioned that there is an ID a
unique ID called Cal access committee ID
that corresponds to the committee ID in
the Committees list so what we're going
to do is we're going to merge these two
data frames so that everything
so that every person who contributed it
to this specific committee will be added
into this new data frame
does that make sense this is just like
joining tables and SQL if you guys have
ever taken two SQL tables and join them
together or like doing a vlookup in
Excel where the two things come together
the unique identifiers in each table
link up
and then you only keep the ones that
match so the Venn diagram of the two
tables are merged and it's just those
ones in the middle that share an ID that
remain
that's a that's an inner join basically
if you're thinking about it
so I'm going to do a pandas merge
command
and
we're going to name this new data frame
that we're going to create from this
join merge so let's
emerged
and then in pandas if you want to merge
two data frames you just do pd.merge
and open and close parentheses and then
you're going to put your arguments
inside this open and close parentheses
so I'm going to try to merge this my
committee's data frame which only
includes committees that have you know
supported or opposed this proposition
into the contributors list data frame so
what this will do is essentially it'll
go through the my committees and look at
this Cal access committee ID
like one three eight one eight zero
eight and try to find that exact ID on
the contrib list and then attach that to
the data frame
so to do that
we're going to merge my committee's data
frame which is called my committees
and we're going to merge that with
contriblist
and then you're going to tell pandas
what do we want to merge these two data
frames on and that's just called on
and we know what it's called it's called
Cal axis prop ID right you could type
that or Cal access committee's ID excuse
me
you could type that up or you could copy
it
and paste it
and this merge will work cleanly because
the two data frames both have this
column called Cal access committee ID
but sometimes when you have two data
frames and you want to merge on a column
and they have different names you can
also specify that saying things like
let's say like on my committees the Cal
access committee ID was called like just
committee ID then in pandas you can kind
of specify which I which columns that
they could merge on by saying things
like left on or right on
but in this case the data frame has
exactly the same name of the columns
that we want to merge on so we can just
name the column
if we look at the merged
data frame
oop okay so a lot of times when I do
pandas because I'm trying to type really
fastly uh really fast a lot I get like a
lot of errors
so whenever you get an error like don't
freak out just like read the error so
right now it's saying data frame object
has no attribute hat I obviously like
spelled head Raw
that's why it's occurring so just
correct that and then you're good
so now if we look at this merge data
frame we can see that on the left side
it's kind of exactly the same as my
committee state of frame right it has
like Cal access prop ID it has the
proposition name
um and it has the committee name
but on the left on the right side it's
The Columns that was the columns that
were present on the contrib list data
frame right
so we have the filing ID the date it was
received the contributor's name the
contributor's first and last name and
all their information right so now the
two data frame has joined as one and it
has become like a really long data frame
that has both of the columns together
now if you notice I don't know if you've
noticed this but here we have like a new
column name
it says committee's name X and this is
because the two data frames that we
merged my committees and my
and the contrib list had a same column
name if you look at
so if you look at the my committee's
columns there is a column called
committee name the contribute list also
has a column called committee name right
so in order to not mix these up pandas
what it does it just attaches the suffix
so I know the X came from the left side
data frame and I know the Y name came
from the right side of the data frame
however they should kind of match up
because we're talking about the same
same proposition here
or the same committees here but that's
why this column name has changed
any questions so far
now if we look at our merged column
merged data frame now our data frame has
kind of increased in size with 860 new
entries can you guys guess why
um there's more personal contributions
than committees exactly so there were
only 11 committees I believe right so
there were only 11 committees but many
many people are contributing to each
different committee so for every every
like 5 10 20 people that contributed to
like this specific committee pandas has
created Rose
for that contributor's name if that
makes sense
so we will still have only like 11
different committees but the people who
contributed to that will add more
committee names does that make sense
so now that we have merged data frame
what does this contain this information
contains every committee and every
person that donated to this specific
committee so now we're going to work
with this merged data frame to get more
information about it okay
so now we're moving on to chapter nine
so
first we're going to start
by doing some math on
the amount of money that was spent to
each of these committees so if you look
at our merged data frame it has this
column called the amount and this is the
amount of money that each contributor
donated to a specific committee
so
this is
similar to when we sum the series in the
beginning of this class so we're just
going to call on that column
merged and we know how to call the
column by saying dot so we're going to
do the data frame name and we're going
to put the column name the amount
and then we're going to call sum
right
and what this does is it goes through
this merge data frame takes all the
numbers in this amount column and sums
it up all together
and now we can see that there have been
what 35
million dollars spent
right so I'm going to be like hey Ben
guess what I found out in 2016 there
were 35 million dollars spent on this
proposition can you believe it I'm gonna
tweet this out put it in the headline
yeah and then Ben's gonna be like
not so fast my friend all right exactly
yes and this is where we can there's a
couple uh like quirks about how campaign
Finance systems work that I think it
might be worth pausing and just passing
on to others in case they haven't which
is uh one as you're like pedantic editor
I'd be like well technically Iris it's
not how much they spent it's how much
they raised right because because this
is the contributions table right and
then there's a very Persnickety
particular thing about campaign
contributions that every newbie has to
learn but like nobody teaches you which
is not all contributions are disclosed
right so when you get a list of campaign
donors like this from a committee right
it is not every donor it is only donors
who gave enough money to trigger the
reporting threshold right and in every
state and in every race and in every
campaign Finance scheme there's a
minimum amount of money that's set and
only people who give more than that
amount of money have their identity
revealed typically and so when you're
looking at an itemized contribution like
this list like this in most cases it's
only going to be the people who gave
more than that amount of money and
therefore if you add up the sum it's
actually not the total right it's only
the total among the people who gave more
I think in this case than one hundred
dollars right and all the people that
gave less than that have their identity
shielded from disclosure and their money
just goes into a lump sum of quote un
itemized contributions and so when
you're covering a campaign or looking at
a committee to understand the total
amount of money that they've raised you
need to look at the totals that they
report on different parts of their form
which are called cover sheets and there
they'll they'll report a big lump sum of
the total amount they raised how much
was itemized like the ones we're looking
at here and how much remained un
itemized because the names were never
disclosed and so in this case 35 million
is not the grand total we would be wrong
to report that it is the total amount of
money from itemized donors and if you've
read campaign Finance stories Through
The Years you may have noticed that uh
that journalists like Derek have to have
come up with a like
um lingo to sort of talk around this
problem okay have you ever noticed
people talk about large donors to a
presidential campaign and they'll refer
to this group of people as large donors
or small donors right that language is
almost always just an attempt to
humanize this legal distinction of which
donations are itemized and therefore we
know the identities and which are
unotomized and we do not know the
identities right and so in this case
what the correct thing for Iris to tweet
would be that there were 35 million
dollars contributed by what we would
call large donors or people who gave
more than one hundred dollars is a
hundred dollars a large amount of money
debatable right
but that's those are quirks and those
are going to be present in almost every
campaign Finance database including the
one where you live and so you just have
to be careful about that and kind of get
a grip on that and recognize it when you
work with it
um there are quirks to this the ACT blue
database that powered the Bernie Sanders
Campaign which was mostly small donors
did end up disclosing all of the small
donors through a strange pass-through
mechanism that they had to use to move
the money and so it's not all as
universally true sometimes you can learn
the small donors
um but
we don't need to get into it okay thank
you
great so I'm okay well now I know then
that 35 million doesn't cover everyone
um so like Ben said this information
usually includes people who have donated
100 or more so we could kind of check
that out so maybe if I pull on the
column once again merged amount and I
called the Min it's going to give me the
minimum value in this column so let's
check
oh
it's a negative number what
does anybody know why
um because it was charged the wrong
account
maybe maybe that's the root cause but
what we know from what's disclosed is
that this was money that was returned to
the donor right and so with it because
we have to remember that these systems
that we're studying are accounting
systems they're not really public
disclosure systems right and so they
include things like correct Corrections
so if someone wants their money back or
has their money refunded because Iris
does a story about how they're a
criminal you know what I mean or
whatever that might be charged as a
negative value into into the itemized
contributions right
um there's cases where people give too
much money there's the legal cap on how
much they can give and they just
accidentally give too much I mean it
happens they might have that charged
back down
um there's other reasons why it happens
Derek can probably rattle some off but
this is another Quirk that you have to
keep in mind is that we were thinking
um maybe we could count this table and
say how many contributions there were
right well we can't because some of them
actually are contributions they're funds
right and so there's just these these
little accounting complexities you have
to you know you have to kind of wise up
to
and and work around and and you can
great so now that we know the quarks of
this data um this data that we're
dealing with let's try to filter our
merged database into the Committees that
support and committees that oppose this
proposition so if you look at the
columns here there is a column called
committee position and it tells us if
this committee is for or against
proposition 64. so in theory right now
you're seeing all the ones that support
but in theory there are ones that
support and oppose and we're going to
break them apart and put them into
separate data frames okay
so another way to check that would be
merged
committee
position
value counts right
looks like I spilled this one
position okay
all right so if we look at the value
counts of this specific column we see
that there are 762 entries where the
committee's position says support and 98
entries where it says a post so we're
going to break this and set it as
separate data frames
so it's kind of similar to what we did
when we filtered on the proposition name
first we're going to create a data frame
that has to do with the committee where
the committee's position is support so
we're just going to name that support
and we're going to filter this merge
data frame on the column committee
position
where this column committed position is
named support or the value is support
and they have to be exactly the same
the way it's written otherwise it'll
break
and we're going to set that aside as its
own data frame we're going to create
another data frame called a pose where
let's just copy this
were the committee's position is not
support but opposed
and then we are going to create another
another data frame
so if you look at support
[Applause]
it's 762 entries that checks out because
there were 762 entries in the data frame
that it was filtered from right
now we are going to run the sum once
again to see how the committee's
Committees who support and oppose raise
different amounts of money
so I wonder if one of our students knows
what's to type oh yeah so if the
question is What's the total amount of
big donor money from the supporting side
what would we type in
support amount some
our support dot amount dot sum
parentheses yeah hell yeah
and we'll do the same for a post
and look at that what are the what are
the numbers there
so it looks like there are more money
going into the support side then yeah
like 32 million to 2.5 million pretty
impressive
so we've already answered a question
right guys it looks like there's a lot
more money on the supporting side than
the opposing side which is a you know an
answer to a question and maybe a lead on
a story yeah so Iris what if I wanted to
figure out like what percentage is that
like I know I could get a calculator out
but I don't know yeah can painters do it
for me yes pandas can do it for you I
would not use a calculator because I
type things very badly
um so let's get the sum here the support
amount sum and we can just do divide it
with the merged amount sum that we got
before right yes and so you see how iris
is using that slash to do the division
that's the built-in python division tool
and so this is a case where we're taking
two like fancy pandas things like a
series sum on both sides and then we're
just putting a very simple python thing
in the middle that division sign
so now we know that 93 of all the money
raised not all the money all the money
raised from large donors there you go
have gone through the support side yep
wow what a finding
I wonder who wrote those chicks
hmm let's figure out
Okay so
we're going to now move on to chapter
10.
uh before we figure it out we're gonna
sort through some of these amounts
so what were some of the 10 biggest
contributions I'm I have a guess that it
came from the support side but let's
just look at it so we're this is how we
found these support versus opposed money
but we're just going to look at the
whole um the all of the money raised
so we're going to go back to our merged
data frame which includes both support
and opposed and we're going to sort the
values
and this is another pandas method
that sorts sorts the data frame on a
specific column and you name the
specific column that you want to sort
the data frame on by putting them inside
of the parentheses here so I am going
back to my merged data frame which looks
like this
right and I want to sort it on the
amount column so as it stands now it's
kind of sorted like haphazardly right
it's like there's a hundred dollars
there's like 25 250 000 but I want to
sort it from top to bottom
so I'm going to write amount here
but if you do at first when you run the
function amount it won't sort
um it will sort from smallest to the
largest so we have to give a specific
argument called ascending false
which means do not do not sort it in
ascending order basically
so now if we look at this data frame we
can see that the amount has been sorted
to the largest to the smallest so the
largest amount given was
four million dollars am I right
and it can just look at the first top
five by calling the method head again
then we can see the top five here
and we can see
that it came from who is this top donor
the name Parker someone named Parker who
lives in Palo Alto one of Cheryl's
neighbors yeah and his first name is
Sean Sean right yeah we just live right
next door to each other I'm sure does
anybody know who Sean Parker is this is
part of the fun of campaign Finance
I just rewatched uh The Social Network
so yeah yeah so he's portrayed by Justin
Timberlake in The Social Network as I
recall and he was the founder of Napster
the notorious MP3 sharing platform and
an early Facebook investor
I believe he had a Game of Thrones
wedding am I getting that right trying
to think of other Sean Parker facts
and uh he contributed four million
dollars in a single check to which side
Iris
looks like the support side
yep and so part of the fun of the of
doing this type of data analysis is
looking in and finding these names and
thinking like don't I know that person
are like can I Google them and so Sean
Parker's brought the biggest check right
yep and we can also see that the top
five largest checks went to the support
side because it's all support support
here right and you'll notice that not
all of them are people there's sort of
an interesting Quirk here that some of
these are non-profit groups like we see
there's the drug policy action
non-profit the fund and this is a common
thing you see in California campaign
finance and elsewhere where um basically
shell organizations are created to move
money between different committees and
propositions and um we won't get to it
as part of this class but if you were to
use other research methods you could
lose you could learn about campaign
Finance you could try to read form 990s
filed with the IRS other disclosure
forms available on the state of
California website and you would learn
that the gentleman named George Soros is
the ultimate source of the funds for
that group
great
um so
because the support site is so big this
is already kind of giving us the top
five support side large donors but we
can also run that a different way which
is getting to our support data frame
which only has the support side and kind
of running the exact same court code
foreign
ascending
false
and let's look at the head
and again Sean Parker up top
and now we can look the opposing side by
going to our oppose data frame which
only has the opposed
contributions
I think I named it a pose
and we can see that on the post side
the largest amount given was a million
dollars
from Julie Oaks
in Pennsylvania
so Julie I mean sorry Julie sure sorry
from Oaks Pennsylvania right and so this
is another like fun thing about going in
this it's like the top donor is a person
who lives in Pennsylvania who is listed
as retired who I've never heard of
I mean top four donors looks like yep
and so Julie Schauer um if you were to
Google her you could read some
interesting interviews she's done with
High Times magazine in other places but
they were all done mostly after this
election and so to me this is a case
where by just fiddling around figuring
out how the top donors did we uncovered
this interesting person Julie shower
someone who doesn't live in California
who's willing to spend at least a
million dollars to prevent marijuana
legalization there and um no one wrote
about her there was not a profile there
was not a story nothing was done and her
identity and what she was doing was was
hidden in plain sight in these databases
and there just weren't any reporters in
California who had the skills and time
and like kind of interest to to push it
down and just by doing just this very
simple analysis that we're doing here
you can uncover stories like this for
yourself in the areas that you cover
just like who gave the most what's the
big check let's Google them figure it
out call him on the phone bam you know
and also looks like Julie gave once in
July
2016. July 20th and also again in July
25th are they the same person we don't
know we'll have to check but
looks like they they could be
all right so now that we know
um the amounts that went to oppose and
support were going to try to rank
we're going to do another thing called
pandas Group by and this is a panda's
message that allows you to group a data
frame by a specific column and then
calculate anything from like a sum to
mean
um to for each grouped
set grouped column if that makes sense
okay Yep this is just like a pivot table
in Excel where you take something that
has one row per item or check in this
case and then you're going to roll it up
using one of the other columns to get
totals by name or state or whatever else
right so let's say in this case Iris
came to be her editor and was like Sean
Parker's number one donor four million
bucks and then she showed me this and I
said well yeah but are you sure he gave
the most overall because I mean that's
just one check it could be this
non-profit wrote five or six checks that
added up to more money right so if we're
going to figure that out we gotta group
the checks together and add them all up
right and that's what we can do next yes
um so let's so you can Group by any
column really
um but first I am kind of seeing that in
the supporting and opposing side there
are a lot of other people from other
states kind of contributing it seems
like so I want to know um if I can Group
by the contributors estate and see how
much money is coming from that each
state right
so a group Buy in pandas so I'm going to
go back to my merged one merge data
frame that has both support and opposed
also we're on chapter 11 now by the way
if you are following along
um I'm going to do merged
Group by
and I'm going to group by here
and put in a column name
so if I look at my I'm just going to
take a peek at my merge data frame again
I want to group by
this column called contributor state
so if I do a merged Group by contributor
State you can see nothing really happens
it just pandas has created the groups
but it doesn't know what to do with them
so it's kind of like waiting further
instructions so what I want to do I want
to group by the state and for every
group so I'm guessing there's a group of
CAS group of Pas group of like you know
Virginia's we are going to group them
and we are going to take that column
amount
and I want to sum them all up so I can
see where the money came from each on
the state that is available in this data
frame okay
so if we do this
and then I'm just going to try to make
it look at pretty so I can do reset
index then the pandas will put it back
into this like pretty data frame format
and I can see that many different states
in fact 29 different states have
contributed to this proposition
I have
a suspicion that California will come up
top but we can also kind of take a look
at that
[Applause]
the virus wants to take this list and
rank the states by which gave the most
money
she she needs to use a trick that we've
already used so far in class and apply
it to this data frame does anybody know
what it is
values
that's almost it
search values
on parentheses
the amount
ascending goals exactly yes you need to
use that sort values function to Resort
it in descending order using the amount
column and this is a case like so many
with pandas were to like take that next
step to ask that next question is just
to chain on another one of these little
tricks you've learned right so we
learned how to sort before now we can
take that trick and we can use it with
the group thing and boom you know what I
mean we can answer this next question
so what's the answer so it looks like
California did contribute the most uh
raise the most and then next it came
from Delaware New York DC all the way
down to
a b what's a b
is that Kansas
great question I don't know Alberta
Maybe
we will have to explore this so you know
if you wanted to figure it out you could
try to freelance and write a filter
right on your data frame to find that
record that's how you would like ask
that question it's the same filter we
wrote before different column different
input right it'll be like merged
contributor
yep
day equal equal a b you see how she's
doing this
and this like what iris is doing right
now this is it this is being a panda's
reporter is you're like what's up with
that that's weird let's write a filter
and like look at it and you're like uh
it's an attorney in Calgary what is that
even legal
you know and you can see he had his
money refunded right Iris yep so it
looks like he gave on
June and then he got refunded in July
right so we're just guessing because all
we have before is these records but my
understanding is it's illegal for
foreign Nationals to contribute to
American political campaigns uh and so
my suspicion would be is that the
campaign got the money in through like a
website or something and then they sent
it back when they realized you know they
couldn't accept it
so we could kind of take this to a Next
Level kind of like what Ben said we can
see which contributor have um
donated most and all we have to change
is Group by because like we said like we
saw here Julie's name came up like twice
here
um we know that she gave more than once
um so we can kind of try to find people
that gave more than once and then kind
of sum them up all together and to do
that
um
what do you guys think we should Group
by on
any columns stand out to you that may
give us the identity of the contributor
your last name
right it's a contributor there is two
columns here contributor last name and
contributor first name
I want to hear on the safe side because
names can last names A lot of people
could have like similar last names so I
want to group by on two columns together
the last name and the first name and in
group by we can do that
it's exactly the same code
except
we put two instead of one column we put
two columns in here
and to do that we put it in a list
format so a bracket
and then I can type in here
contributor first name
and then comma
contributor last name
so now I'm going to group on
contributors first and last name
together and we're going to run a sum on
the amount column
so if I do that
oh I got an error because I spelled
contributor wrong
here we go
there we go
so I guess Sean Parker is just giving a
lot of money but also Sean Parker and
Affiliated entities
right so he's in there in two different
ways which makes it kind of tricky you
might need to add those together
yourself or clean up the data
but you know you might look at this Iris
and say yeah Sean Parker's number one
right I add those two together he's
given more than anybody else right
okay you might notice
that there's something wrong
based on what we looked at earlier in
the data that there's something missing
does anybody notice it is it the support
and oppose
well that's true that's not there we
could we could Group by that if we
wanted to you want to add that Iris
sure add committee position to the group
that's like another nice thing
but that will just improve what we have
here it won't fix the hidden mistake
does anyone see it there were Clues
earlier didn't Julie have like a
different
will she listen to something else as
well
sheep might have been but we're not
seeing it here there's something even
worse
well I mean one thing I always
keep in mind with stuff like this is is
um when you're working with a data frame
you can move really quickly you can
group and aggregate a lot of Records
really quickly and things can kind of
fly by and go wrong Without You noticing
and one thing I made sure to point out
earlier when Iris was sorting and
looking at the biggest checks do you
guys remember that list we looked at the
biggest checks and we stopped and looked
at that I always like to stop and look
at things like that as I go and keep
them in mind as I continue my analysis
because sometimes things might go wrong
um when we looked at those biggest
checks remember there was drug policy
action
and these weird non-profit groups that
had written these zillion dollar checks
fund for policy reform and all those
guys like those were multi-million
dollar checks
and they're not in our ranking after we
grouped I mean what's up with that
shouldn't they be there somewhere right
something's got to be wrong and like
this is one of these moments where
you're just like uh your sanity checking
you maybe once you've seen and and
there's a reason why they're not here
and it's not really our fault it due to
it has to do with a quirk in pandas that
I think is really crucial to pass along
to all students of a class like this
Iris you want to explain it
four
so if we look at let's see if it pops up
so we are grouping from this data frame
right so for this committee
um yes on 64 California is to control
and regulate blah blah blah we have a
name associated with it here Laura
Braden but right under it as you can see
right here the
there is a
um a notation Nan which means it's not
um
it's not a number right it's a null
value it's an empty value so when a
value is empty the group by is just
going to ignore this
so what yes are you telling us we'll
just delete the record from it's just
one care and throw it away
exactly and so this is just a really
dumb default in pandas which is if you
Group by a column and there are no
values in that column by default it is
omitted from the result right and it
just so happens in California campaign
Finance when a corporation or a
non-profit makes a donation the name of
the group is put into the last name
field it's like a cluge on their own
database that they wrote right and the
first name field is left null and so the
result of our group by without us really
maybe even thinking about it is that we
lost all corporate and nonprofit
donations accidentally right and so we
have to adjust for that and how we write
our group by an account for it and like
ways you could have identified this
earlier right is one kind of looking at
the data row by row and making sure the
results are what you think they kind of
ought to be like that's how I spotted
this initially but there's other ways
too when we ran those info commands
about our table really early on right
for each column it gives you a number of
how many null values there are right and
so we could see wow look of the 860
entries uh only 750 have a first name
right so that was like a little clue
we've got some nulls like right there
right and when you're working with the
pandas you always you have to keep a
careful eye on these nulls so how do we
how do we avoid this how do we get
George Soros back into the count Iris
yeah so one way we can
um take care of these nulls is there is
a method called fill n a and you can put
this on a column or you can put this all
over a data frame it doesn't
it depends on how you want to use it but
right now I'm going to put it over this
data frame so I'm going to tell pandas
on the merge data frame I want you to
fill all the N A values
and N A essentially is
um is blank but
um
it's like there's nothing in there but I
want you to put something in there even
like a blank text or blank space
whatever and to do that I'm just going
to say fill n a with a blank text
so that it's just filled okay so I'm
going to run this on the whole database
and what it will do is it's going to
identify these nulls in this column as
well as these columns that have the
nulls and just like fill it in with like
empty uh strings empty strings
and remove it from like the void
basically
so I'm just going to put that Command
right before
so that it's filled in and then I'm
going to run the same exact thing so I'm
going to group by contributor first name
last name and committee position
and then take the amount column sum it
all up reset the index and sort values
all at the same time
copying and pasting
like so
if we run this
now we can see sure Sean Parker still
giving a lot of money but the second
most is not or third most depending on
how you see it is not Julie actually
it's fun for policy reform
right and you see if you then account
for these spelling variations and kind
of smooth them out on your own later you
might see that if you took the different
rows for fund for policy reform and
added them together they actually gave
more money than Sean Parker right and so
just that little thing about getting of
dropping a record grouping and Counting
right made the difference between
getting the story right and getting the
story wrong right and so these tools are
really powerful you can move really
quickly but you got to be careful and
you gotta like with each step just make
sure nothing's going wrong
and I think this really shows how we
really have to interview the data like
we would interview any person or source
that we talked to you can't really take
everything for as face value you have to
know the limitations of what it can
provide and possible errors inside
um just because it's numbers it's not
always very straightforward
um well I think that's my part and we
are going to take our findings and put
something presentable together
and it's going to be led by Andrea hi
Andrea
before we move on do you guys have any
questions for us
about what we did so far today
I have a question that you don't need to
answer now but if there's a resource you
could point me to so like this example
that you just pointed to how fun for
policy reform
has it's in there with two different
um titles right I work a lot with school
data and like I'll have two data sets
and this the names are never written the
same way so I have this issue a lot
where could I go to figure out how to
clean that up
in Python
how would you do it Iris
um for me I guess
um
first I want to see how they're all
written differently
so I know that it would have some sort
of like fun policy reform and maybe it
has more or less things so one way to do
that is to filter the data frame but on
a very like a fuzzy kind of matching
like uh
on um pieces of the text if that makes
sense so sometimes I'll look at my data
frame and
and then we can do this command called
string
contains
and then you can kind of put like a
piece of text in there and it will
return anything that's
contains this text okay
this is a pretty cool pandas feature is
you can do little fuzzy searches
so then
um this has returned
here we go now we can see like okay so
this is a one with fun for policy reform
this has returned this one and this has
returned this types so I could kind of
see okay
there's like two different name types
um that's just like for me to know and
another thing you could do perhaps is
um
get all the unique names so I would
call on the column which is
contributor last name
and then I will sort them or
get all the unique values so if you
think it's a new feature how about that
but I could also
sort them so I will sort the data frame
first
sort values
[Applause]
and
contributor last name
and then now it's kind of like sorted
alphabetically so I could kind of like
look at it and see like different
variations like these two look like the
same names but they have like a
different variation right right so
sometimes
so sometimes what I do is I will put
this into
um uh
an Excel spreadsheet literally just like
all the unique names and then I'll go
down each line and say okay for
everything that says drug policy
non-profit 50c Yes on Prop 64. I wanted
to give it like a clean name so I'll
type in a clean name right next to it
and then read that database in and then
merge it yep you can also use open
refine to to Cluster and standardize
names totally this is techniques we do
all the time we call it cleaning the
data or standardizing the data and
iris's technique is just really it it's
like you get the unique list of dirty
names right you then put it into a
spreadsheet into open refine you make
another column and then you you
standardize them so in cases where you
want them to come out the same you give
them the same value in that new column
right you merge that back in and then
you group using the clean column instead
of the dirty column and now they'll add
up
because you'll have the dirty column in
case you want to check your work and
make sure that you didn't screw it up
exactly this is really common with
campaign Finance type stuff I think
people have different slight variations
on how to do it but it's really common
one thing I like to do is when I do that
unique output I like to count the number
of contributions and sum them into the
into the coding sheet because then I can
prioritize the ones that are the most
money because like let's say oh my gosh
there's ten thousand names I'll never be
able to do them all but if you do it
that way you can say well we we
standardized enough to account for 95 of
the money you know what I mean or you
could just focus your efforts on
cleaning up the ones that make the
biggest difference to the output you
know
that was very helpful
and you could do that with all the
techniques we learned here in class you
would group it by the dirty name you
would then use a write function which we
haven't got to yet but that would write
that out to a cdsv you then would do
your cleaning in there you'd read that
CSV back in and then you'd merge it on
and group it
hey Ben uh-huh
uh we've been going for a decent chunk
now it seems like maybe we want to give
people a little bit of a break yeah we
have the chart section coming up right
with Andrea which we're about to break
into what if we took a 10 minute break
and came back and did charts would that
be okay
sounds good and and the other thing is
like we can take a 10-minute break but
if folks have questions they could they
can also hang out here and ask the
questions yeah we can maybe do 15. let's
say we'll start at 10 40 or 12 45
Pacific Andrea will come in and she will
teach you how to make some kick-ass
charts out of this data yet too
thank you Iris thank you
we've got the
the like fun visual part to come so it's
like the dessert it is like the dessert
after all the learning
so for those who hang around if you're
still into it there's a chapter we don't
need to go through in class but it's the
remix chapter if you were to now go back
up higher in your notebook and remember
when we printed out all the props and we
then selected ours and named it as that
my prop variable you remember that if
you were to go up and substitute a
different prop name the cigarette tax
the bag ban the death penalty one
substitute that name into that one
variable and then rerun the whole
notebook from the top you would get the
exact same analysis but for a different
prop
right and that and that this is part of
the power of the notebook right is that
just by
you know scripting it all out you can
repeat it and you can do variations on
it and remix it you know
are the commands uh in in um in this uh
in Panda are they if I'm using a text
editor like Sublime text or something do
I have to learn a whole other language
are they pretty much the same commands
you could run pandas in a traditional
python script that is a text file it
does not need to be run in a jupyter
notebook environment so if you if you
preferred to write like a traditional
python script that was just in a flat
file it would totally work it's just
that each time you wanted to rerun the
code you'd have to run it all from the
top right you know so it would have
would be one chunk of code that could
only be executed like in a bolt which
could be slow and require you doing a
lot more like fiddling and re-running
and losing time where the notebook is
nice is that you can just work on that
one cell you know what I mean and do it
one little itty bitty bit at a time
is it it's just for this is right really
mechanical stuff but um like for fans of
python crash course you know the text
editor Sublime Text
um do they all vary one from the other
uh when you're text editors themselves
yeah
yeah I mean it's just like Coke and
Pepsi it's like different you know
variations on the same flavor got it
yeah the big difference is if you get
into like Microsoft Word or something
where it's formatting the text and has
like stuff like that that's not meant
for code right you want these flat text
editors that are just like you know text
yeah yeah thanks
foreign
other questions
hi can you hear me
okay I just wrote a question in the chat
um but I wanted to see if you could
repeat the kind of best practices
um
um that you were talking about with
cleaning like do you want to export that
and then clean it up and then put it
back in pandas or what do you suggest
I mean Iris what would you say is the
best way to do it if you were being
really good about it
I always keep copy of all the dirty data
as is and then I'll just create a new
data frame and then perhaps I'll match
the new names into that but like Cheryl
said I would still keep the dirty column
I just like to keep everything right
unless I'm presenting something so
you're sort of merging data you're not
overriding it right so you don't lose
what you started with yeah and to me I
think that's a good rule with Jupiter
notebooks in general is that you're
you're not you're not losing anything
along the way you're just annotating and
improving it you know Cheryl what do you
think yeah I'm a hoarder I keep all the
dirty stuff and and then also the the
cleaned up file so yeah because I live
in fear of making a mistake and that way
I can always just check like did I
really merge this properly did I really
sum it you know the right things right
right I mean Joe you're a professor now
what would you advise
well um I think what people said the
biggest thing I think the way I think
about it is that you want to be able to
make sure that you can audit and
reproduce it in case anything goes wrong
both to explain it to your Editor to
explain it to yourself in six weeks if
you have to put the story on hold and so
everything you can do to sort of make
your process methodical and repeatable
which includes not destroying data like
always keeping copies and as is um
Central to alike about it I I would add
that and the nice thing about the
Jupiter notebook is you're not but even
then like when you if you save a a
notebook like give it a good name
structure right it's like you don't want
final final Final on your name you don't
want like five Untitled notebooks I'm
guilty of that yeah okay you know the
notebook is really uh this is
I'm gonna reveal how pretentious I am
maybe here but I think the notebook is
like an emerging form of literature I'll
be totally honest with you
um and I think that the standards and
structure for it is still fluid in an
experimental State and this is one of
the reasons I really like reading
different people's notebooks because I
think there's a lot of experimentation
going about how to structure them you
know like for me personally the thing
that I've kind of stumbled into that I
like is is
um having multiple notebooks that
operate in the sequence you know so
rather than having like one huge
notebook that has 8 000 lines of code
and has like my all the little diddles I
did along the way like strewn throughout
there that's like the first draft and
then the second draft is like 1 one
little notebook that just downloads the
data and writes it to a CSV like then a
next notebook that takes that data and
cleans it up and like does the tidying
and then outputs a tidy CSV right and
then like a third notebook maybe that
then analyzes that tidy CSV and so that
I'm able to sort of like separate the
stages of the kind of pipeline of the
data into little discrete chunks so that
they kind of can like I don't know just
make it it works better for me mentally
you know I've been completely uh copying
you in that band because I I yeah I
think you've mentioned that to me before
and it's so much more useful this is
just easier for me to get my head around
it
I do see why it's called notebook now
there's a lot of almost like scribbling
of figuring out what you want to do it
is
for me I'm when I was a student I did
have a class and learned a little bit
about open refine and so I feel
comfortable cleaning with that so if I
were to start kind of querying data like
we did today and then realize I need to
group some stuff together I could put
that in open refine and then do you
recommend starting a I guess we'll learn
how to for sure save a jupyter notebook
here today but then I could start a new
notebook and and have that clean kind of
sheet and it would just be like the
little Gap in the pipeline you know what
I mean there's like there's the python
part of the pipeline then there's your
open refine part and then you pick it
back up with the next thing yeah gotcha
okay thank you guys the other thing I
would add two more things and that is
that um
I I comment that I mean like I just I
like really clear commenting right
because I just think especially when I'm
because I'm teaching when I'm teaching
students like they may be their first
time and looking at a Jupiter notebook I
just want a lot of really clear
instructions for somebody who might be
coming brand new to it so they could
treat it almost like a tutorial totally
and so there's that and then I think
there's the hey what's the final you
know especially for the analysis ones
like what's the published version what's
the one that I'm going to put out there
for anybody to access and kind of walk
through those steps what that needs to
be nice and neat less of a scribble yep
and I I think to get to that point
there's almost always like three at
least three drafts of the notebook you
know you know what I mean there's that
that first one where you're just like uh
what is this and thrashing and writing
all this stuff and then you kind of like
can break that into pieces so you sort
of like Get Your Arms Around what you're
doing but then there's this moment I
think all danger journalists know where
you sort of like I call it when you cut
and run where it's like you've done all
this fit you've looked at all this
different stuff but like this is the
story and like all that other stuff
you know what I mean and like
and to me there's like the third final
version of The Notebook it's like I'm
just gonna take out all the experiments
and it's just going to be a pipeline
that goes to the published work of what
I publish you know what I mean and that
it's until I get to that point I kind of
hate my notebook like that's when I feel
good about it
Andrea how do you how do you set them up
uh badly
um
I I always mean to go back and and
re-order refactor I I try to do any kind
of data set manipulation in one notebook
and then the actual analysis and
visualizations in a different notebook
um if if there are like multi multiple
prongs to like you know there's like a
um you know something I'm working on for
like
for that's sort of like a fundamentally
different analysis but for the same
story right um I've found it's good to
break that up into multiple notebooks
um but I would definitely
also emphasize the commenting thing not
just for other people reading your work
but if you come back to this notebook in
six months you're not gonna remember why
you filtered the way you did or groups
the way you did
um so using comments within your code
cells but also using that markdown
function where you can switch a cell to
a text cell basically
um and just like write down what you're
doing and why
um if there's a part where you're
exporting exporting a CSV cleaning it in
open refine and then bringing it back in
write that down right
um
otherwise like it's a favor to yourself
for the future totally I think you know
there's a way in which you can feel like
you're showing off with your notebook
but you're actually helping yourself
more than anything else I think that
that's so true and I think a lot of the
times those notes aren't really
technical notes they're more like things
from your reporting like you learned we
have to exclude these records for some
weird reason you know what I mean and
like are you gonna remember that weird
reason you know it's like it's really
good to write it down
other questions
um
I might have missed it but I had asked
in the chat is there a way to keep track
of the different variables and things
that you're defining as you're going
along and even just in the tutorial I
was like did I make a variable for that
do we have a data frame for that
um so would you do that in like a
separate area I can python just kind of
spit out here's everything you've
defined so far
so python doesn't do it but notebooks do
it there's a so we haven't really talked
about magic but there's this whole class
of things you can do a notebook called
magix that are commands that begin with
a percent so you can do percent LS and
type return and it's just type just like
you type LS in the terminal uh and you
can do a bunch of others and one that
you can do is present who who like who's
in the room and I will show you all the
variables that you've defined during the
current that are currently defined in
this session I don't actually use it
much but it's kind of interesting but I
think the main thing if you think about
sort of the processes we've been talking
about at the end of the day they'll all
be there in your notebook and it's you
can certainly like hop around and do
things out of order which can be
confusing but I think I saw someone
mention in the chat like you kind of
want to try and have discipline that
says everything goes from the top and
goes to the bottom so that if I do quit
and start over and run it again it'll
come out the way I want and so then
you'll pretty much be able to see the
variables and you'll learn some tricks
about like white space and formatting
and commenting to make that more clear
so that who actually is not as handy as
it sounds but if you're if you really
are just kind of like bopping around
exploring stuff it can be handy
[Music]
it's actually a pretty cool one there's
a sequel magic so if you do the right
setup stuff you can actually run that
Ben mentioned and this is actually it's
true that you can just do pd.read SQL
and get a data frame from a database but
you can also just do the SQL right there
in a Cell yeah and that's that's kind of
nice we might be showing our age with
that one though Joe what SQL yeah I know
well if you want to learn C so this is
this is our fun uh people this took off
way more than I thought of it but if you
don't do Sequel and and you didn't get
to learn a night card this year check
out
mystery.nightlab.com for a little fun
SQL tutorial
um that might entertain you yeah
Hey Joe could I ask a follow-up question
on that actually sure
um because one of the things when I was
first starting out with a lot of This
was um just the like I I kind of also
ran into that that weird thing where I
get kind of like I like to see
everything that I have like visually in
the IDE
um which is why I like loved our studio
so much because it would it has like I
think a little just especially if you're
like getting used to the GUI like it has
just like it's more visual uh is is
there a resource of all of those like
that percent who or percent LS is their
resource of all of those commands
because I feel like that would help me
kind of like make the transition to a
python notebooks or just like help them
work help me work with them a little bit
better I mean I don't think there's a
resource as nice as what you're
imagining
um although actually the help in
Notebook is pretty good if you notice um
on there's a help menu uh that has a
handful of things I don't think any of
them is actually a magic reference yeah
but there is like a reference for
keyboard shortcuts which I like a lot
I'm a very much a keyboard guy
um so definitely know about that um but
yeah I think mostly if you probably
Googled for uh pandas sell Magic or iPad
I think it would be IPython so the
interactive python is the version that
runs the notebook IPython yeah that's
right that's right so I think I python
Magics would probably get you the list
um if you're a super debugger like oh my
God I love debugging tools there's
actually one of the newest things in
Jupiter that's like brand new is there's
a debuggable version of IPython I don't
even know how to pronounce it it's
spelled x-e-o-n Xeon or something and
you could if you install this extra
python add-on in your notebook you can
create
um a notebook where the individual cells
will have like much more Trace backing
and debugging kind of possibilities
oh I didn't know about that one of the
Magics is pdb yeah probably most people
here are not python programmers yet but
pdb is a python debugging tool and you
can throw that in and kind of get it to
stop when an error happens and do a
little bit of an inspection without even
installing anything else just
um but that's probably not something
most of you want to get into anytime
soon
because
now Iris put a cheat sheet in the chat
um as you were talking about structuring
your different Jupiter notebooks is it a
situation where you would like do one
process start a new notebook and have to
kind of input what you import what you
did before to keep going in order to
that's what it ends up having to be Yeah
you sort of have to hand things off you
know what I mean and like there's
different philosophies about this but
what I like to do is like have every
notebook reads and files and writes out
files you know what I mean in in that
way it's kind of like functional
programming in the old school way you
know where and so like so to me it's
like well my downloader is going to read
from the web and write to a raw data
directory and the cleaner is going to
read from the raw directory and write to
the clean directory and then the
analysis one's going to read out of that
is how I often do it but I'm sure
there's other approaches that's just one
way
it's good to think about maybe folders
where you put raw files and then like
clean files a lot of different folders
just to keep them tidy I guess I mean
it's really up to you sometimes like my
notebooks I like get to start with like
zero one and then I'll put a name on it
like clean up zero two I don't know
analysis just so that it even looks like
it's in order just for my like visual
sanity you know and you can actually
write meta notebooks that run other
notebooks if you really want to get into
it that's one of the magic commands
um just just real quickly on that last
Point
um I was wondering if there's any kind
of conventions or like standards in
regards to how you should write and then
call functions within a notebook
um like should you write like a full
function at the top and then call it
later on or should you like write it in
place where you're going to use it or
anything like that
I don't think I think people kind of
it's the wild west you know what I mean
like one feature we're not going to
cover here in this class is the apply
function which is a really common pandas
tool and this is where you iterate over
a column or over the data frame and then
you you map every value through a
function right so let's say you have
like a a cleaner function or a data type
conversion function and you want to run
everything in a Cell through everything
in a column through it right you you do
dot apply and then you give it the name
of the function and boom it'll just map
them all right and so a common pandas
pattern that's out there is you write
the little function in the cell just
like a standard python function and then
you apply it in the next cell like
you'll see a lot of people do that
all right yeah thank you yeah there's
cases where we'll we'll write the
function in like a flat python file and
just import it at the top too like you
know if it's a really long gnarly
function you know that might be nice
or if you're going to reuse the function
across notebooks like
um so like you know our coronavirus
tracker is just like 50 Jupiter
notebooks that do a bunch of stuff in
order but we have common functions for
reading and writing files to the data
directories so those functions like sit
in a little flat python file and then
the other notebooks kind of import them
and use them you know
Ben I've wondered about that so do you
script the execution of that or does
somebody want to watch those while they
run just to make sure everything is
going right it's a mix
um uh
we have GitHub actions so we have sort
of scheduled tasks that run in the cloud
that execute the notebooks and we've
gradually moved to a system where the
different data sources are sort of their
own modules or apps so there's like a
little app that is the data pipeline for
the state prison data that Iris must of
and there's another one that's for the
HHS Hospital data or for the the
unemployment data and each of those
little modules will have a download
notebook and a processing notebook right
and then those those notebooks will get
run as part of the module in the little
scripted like cron and for the ones that
are kind of like pure scrapers and set
and forget we just let the computer do
it and it'll howl if something goes
wrong we put a lot of assertion tests in
right like things to like make sure
something hasn't gone wrong right but
then in the case of our data entry for
cases and deaths we actually
um do that we we we watch that one
because that's kind of the most
sensitive one with a lot of human data
entry
thanks yeah I never really thought about
executing notebooks automatically just
because I know a different way to get
the same thing done but I I can see why
that would be valuable if that's how you
start just to not have to read exactly I
mean it's a whole world like running a
notebook from a script or a scheduled
task is a whole thing and it's actually
pretty bad at it Jupiter by default is
it cannot be run really from the
terminal
um there are huge Frameworks for uh
scripting them there's one called paper
mill which is just so overblown and
Bloated it's like kind of worthless I
think but I think that that's what runs
inside of Netflix or runs inside of the
marketing operation at A T or or credit
fraud detection at Chase they have like
these paper mill notebook like like
pipelines but uh for us we just have
like a little a little command line
wrapper we wrote that'll just run them
um but that even writing that's more of
a hassle than it ought to be
um okay I've probably drafted on too
long there and I think we're we're past
our break and so I would like to
introduce Andrew suazzo from Vermont
uh live and direct who is going to guide
you through the remainder of our class
which is how to install Altair and make
beautiful charts take it away
yeah
um so we are actually at a little bit of
a different spot than the first python
notebook walkthrough has a set but it's
actually great because it'll let us do a
couple of additional fun things
um without remaking a uh data frame so
that's exciting
um
let me just get my windows set up
uh
screen there we go
okay
here we go okay can you all see my
notebook screen
okay
all right
so I am uh actually doing something that
you're not supposed to do which is I
didn't rename my notebook it's still
Untitled so don't do what I do
um
because then you'll never remember
whether you did your analysis and I'm
Untitled Untitled one Untitled two
Untitled three
could be anything
um okay so the first thing that we're
gonna do though is
um actually save your notebook
and
um pop back to and you can just close
that window open your
um terminal up again
and shut down that uh that notebook
server that you were running
um
so
um what we need to do now actually is uh
we need to oh
um so to save it you should it should
auto save but I usually just hit like
command s before I close out a window
and that should work for you
um
and it should also give you a warning if
you try to close it and you haven't
saved
save um hopefully
um so uh you should get back to your
terminal and
um and you can exit that by
um I mean I know it's control
I think it's Ctrl C Ctrl D on a Mac
um probably something similar on Windows
but just get back to your control C okay
um so just get back to that
um
that uh
uh command line where you can actually
enter
um enter commands and we are going to
install a new library
um so similar to what we've done before
pip and install
um and this is Altair
and that is our data visualization that
library that we're going to be using um
it is a relatively new library
um uh it will
um
it'll export
uh
like interactive images for you
um in in your Jupiter notebook that are
actually like JavaScript
um uh visualizations and we'll talk a
little bit about the like like things
you can once you have created them but
functionally in our notebook they're
going to be like basically glorified
images
um
so once you have installed that um it
should be ready to um go in your
environment
um and you're just gonna we're just
gonna start back up our uh Jupiter lab
notebook again
um this just to make sure you remember
how to do this because this is a good
thing to do over and over again a couple
times so you don't forget it
and of course it's opening in the wrong
Windows there we go Andrew we had a
requests in the comments if you could
bump the size of your browser font oh
yes of course
Okay so we've got a new uh Jupiter lab
or we've got our old Jupiter lab uh
notebook
um
and I have this fun little error that's
not causing any issues but that seems to
have to do with the new MacBooks but
um
uh so we have uh we have our import
pandas
um
uh command up here uh you're gonna we're
gonna have this these number readouts
um which kind of makes it look like we
have not yet run uh that like we have
already read these cells into uh into
your compute our computer's memory
that's not the case
um so if I hop down to committee list
and try to run it
um I get PD is not defined because I
have not yet uh read the pandas library
in here
um so we're gonna need to run all of
these cells again in order to be able to
use any of the variables
um
and a handy way to do that actually
um is run all cells in the Run menu
um which will just go through and run
everything
um and I'm just gonna do that to read
everything back in
um but the one uh the one thing we're
gonna add here
um and technically we could do this
anywhere in our document as long as we
read you know as with any variable if we
run the cell we have that variable to
use anywhere in the cell
um but usually we're going to import our
libraries at the top of the notebook
um
so here I'm going to add an import line
um and it's going to be Altair
um and just like with pandas we're
actually going to give it kind of a
nickname
um that makes it a little easier to type
over and over again
um and that is going to be as Alt
um so when we want to use any Altera
commands
um to make a chart uh we can we just
have to
um use the alt shortcut
um and then if you re-run that uh
even if you've hit run all cells you
rerun that we now have Altair that we
can use
um
and I'm just gonna scroll all the way
down
um and so now I can use Altair anywhere
in this document
um we're gonna hop down to our
um our merged data set here
um and
we uh we sort of ran it so that we could
um pop it out into the cell see what was
in it
um but we didn't actually give it a
variable name
um and in order to uh in order to
visualize the stuff in here we're going
to want to give it a name
um so let's call this top contributors
top contributors equals
I'm just gonna
um
also pop out the head just to make sure
that what I think I saved uh to this
data frame is in fact what I saved
um make sure that you have those blank
first names in there again
um uh that you're using this fill-in
fill in a to uh prevent that group by
from dropping any of your stuff
um because we definitely want to keep
those in there
okay
um so we have all the all the
um setup that we need to be able to look
at
um
uh this in a way that is not just like a
table
um so what we can do is start main chart
and to make any Altair chart uh
the basic
um syntax is alt dot chart the C is
capitalized
um and before we go any further we can
just run that and see what it says
um so the error we get here is that data
is a required property
um which we can probably guess means it
wants a data set to actually be able to
uh visualize
so let's pop in our data set
um
I'm just going to run that again
um so this time we get a different error
and that error is Mark is a required
property
um
what that means what mark means in the
context of Altair
um is how do you want me to show the
show the numbers basically so Altair has
a lot of different marks that are
possible you can say like Mark Circle
Mark line mark
uh
I think the map is Mark Geo
um but in this case we're just gonna say
Mark underscore bar
um and it's it's always going to follow
that uh basic syntax so Mark underscore
and then the thing the kind of chart
type
to do
um
and then we get a shirt type and we're
gonna run that and we got a nice little
box
um
and so that doesn't look like a bar
chart but that is a really good sign
um because it means that it has a data
set and it has a way that it's supposed
to chart the data
um and it is ready for us to uh to kind
of give it more instructions it's no
longer an error
um but it's just sort of arbitrarily
giving us a made-up like box because it
doesn't actually have data to chart
um and to pass in some data for it to
show
um we're gonna add on and encode
function
um
and within in code we're just going to
pass in like a list of the instructions
um so this is where you're gonna give it
anything it needs to plot
um
um so the first thing we want to do
um is give it the like most basic
building blocks of a chart are usually
going to be the X and the y axis
um so in order to pass in what we want
uh to tell it what we want on that X and
Y axis
um we're going to take a look at our
chart and in this case we're going to
look at
um because contributor first name has a
lot of blanks
um
we're gonna say contribute or last name
we know that field is filled out in
almost every case in every case because
we looked at those uh we looked at that
um data frame info
um and then for why we need a number
value
um
and in this case we're going to say
amount
and this is going to give us like a
really really really long
uh chart
not really useful for anyone uh in any
sense
um but actually uh we have our we have
saved this top contributor contributors
data frame
um sorted
um so we already have it sorted first to
last
um and so we actually have a way of just
showing the like those highest values in
this data frame pretty easily
um can anybody think of what we might do
to uh tell Altair to only chart the like
first maybe five rows
uh the head command with uh uh
parentheses
yes indeed
yeah so um so actually this is uh this
is like a step before Altair so what we
can do is just edit that sort of like
pass in a different version of that
Panda's data frame
by just tacking that head onto the end
of the data frame that we're we're
telling altered a chart
um
so that's great we got our top
contributors
um
and we got uh
we got them sorted in
an order that's not really very useful
visually
um but we're like we're we've got a good
start
uh if we wanted to kind of uh widen out
what we're looking at we could actually
type in another number into head and so
head defaults to the first five
um but we could say 10 and then it'll
give us the like top 10
um values in that data frame
um
and then
the other thing that we might want to do
kind of before we look at sorting for
readability here
um is to change uh change where these uh
change which axes are showing up
um often especially if you have really
long text
um it's like kind of mean to make your
reader uh like tilt their head to
actually read uh read the important
information on the chart which is who
actually is giving this money
um so in this case
it might be maybe a little more readable
a little more friendly to
um the person who's going to end up
looking at this chart
um to just switch around X and Y
um and as you can see here it doesn't
matter which order you tell out there
um to uh which order you pass in the uh
encoding variables
to Altair you can
put X first you can put y first
um
uh what really matters is just like
the why the y-axis is is the vertical
axis the x-axis is the horizontal axis
and what what column names you're
telling it to plot there
um so this is great this is actually
um this is looking a lot closer to a
chart that like we could maybe hand to
an editor
um
but there's still some kind of uh visual
um issues
and one of uh one of those issues
um I would say
is that it's like pretty hard to derive
any information from
um a chart that is in this order
um and the order that Altera is actually
defaulting to
um here is alphabetical order
um so given no other information
um Altair will always sort the y-axis by
the Y values right
and so the Y values are string values so
it defaults to alphabetical order for
string values
um we don't actually want that because
that's not useful I'm I don't like parse
this information in alphabetical order I
want to see who gave the most money
um
so to do that we have to use a little
bit more kind of um an expanded Syntax
for Altair
um
so it's very very easy
um to just like pass in a column name
um to Altair and it'll like try to guess
what you want it to do
um and like we have a pretty usable
chart
um but if we want to pass it additional
information
um we can use a slightly longer syntax
um and once again we're using that alt
shortcut that we declared earlier
um so we are now saying
um create a y-axis
um
and the first argument is always the
column name
um but then after the first argument we
can pass in additional arguments to
customize how how this chart appears
um and in this case
um we're gonna pass in a sort argument
um so there are some like kind of
complicated things that you can do with
the sort Fields you can declare custom
orders you can do sort of like
um kind of uh like
Things based on
um you know things based on like
groupings bins categories
um but in this case we actually just
want to sort
um the y-axis by the x-axis values
um right so we already have uh we have
already declared the x-axis
um so if we just pop in sort equals X
and that X is going to be in quotations
um it will sort by our access
this is a relatively new trade it's like
the year and a half old and it used to
be way harder to sort a chart in out
there
um so this is very exciting
still
um and then to reverse that order you
can just put a negative sign before that
X
um and we get our highest value at the
top
and so we know that we saw from sorting
our data frame that um Sean Parker was
at the top there so this is sort of
confirming what we've already figured
out
um
but in a way that gives us a little bit
more of a like visual representation of
like what the scale of these donations
are
um and again
like we discussed earlier we do have
Sean Parker in here twice
um and that is definitely something that
is not like ideal
um but that's something that that you
would want to sort of clean
um in one of those ways that we talked
about
um and then you could chart your cleaned
data sets
um but we're good we're not gonna uh
kind of touch that today
um so the next thing that we probably
want to do to get like a production
ready chart
um is to make these names a bit more
readable
um and so that to do that we're actually
going to go back to pandas and we're
gonna do something
um that we haven't done yet which is to
create a new column
um so we have our top contributors
column
or data frame
um and to create a new column
um all you have to do is
um tell it top contributors
um whatever okay contributor
let's say full name
to distinguish it from
first and last name
um so we just give it a column name and
then we say call this column name equals
um and then we tell it
what the sort of formula we want
um is and in this case uh
we already have uh contributor
first name
and
what we can do is add in
um
so so to combine strings you can just
use the plus sign and as long as those
columns are both string columns and not
like a number column that shouldn't give
you an error
it might not give you an error if it
were a number I don't
okay
so we have contributor first name plus
contributor last name
um
in cases where there is no first name
this string will actually just start
with uh space
um which is not ideal but also
um isn't going to have any impact on
like the Integrity of this data so
we're going to say we're okay with that
and then you know we could clean it up
later
so if you run that you should have a new
column
um
that has names that actually look a lot
more
um a lot more kind of uh
like normal names for uh people who are
not organizations
um so we've got Sean Parker in here now
we've got rich Goldberg
um
so that's good so that's that's kind of
a more readable column
and then I'm just gonna copy and paste
what we've already done here
just to keep the order
uh
just so I'm not like defining a new
column and then going back up to an
earlier cell and using that column
um
so here we can just Sub in contributor
full name instead of contributor last
name
and now we have
actual names
um
and so that's we're making a lot of
progress and this is looking like much
more like a chart that you might
um kind of
hand off to your editor once you have
done an analysis you need to like kind
of uh you need some visuals for your
story
um this might be kind of close to what
you're looking for
um but we do have
um
we do another column in here and that's
committee position
um and as we'll recall before actually
we know that Julie's shower
um was one of those folks who was not
um not kind of supporting this ballot
initiative
um but she just want all the rest in
this Visual and that doesn't tell us a
whole lot about uh
that doesn't tell us a whole lot about
like what money is actually going to
um
to kind of which sides of this cause
um so to do that we can actually throw
another layer into this encoding
um definition
and that is just color
one of the nice things about Altair is
that like a lot of stuff is named very
logically so sometimes you can just
guess and it'll work Andrew before we do
this we've had a question come up in the
chat I want to just address which is
some people are having a data type error
on their contributor full name
where the computer it thinks it's a
mixed data type and I think this might
be just a quick moment to show the
Altair shorthand that can solve this
issue so when you're providing that
column into alt Y and you do contributor
full name you can put a colon after full
name
and then the letter N right
and that will tell it that this is a
nominative category not a quantitative
category and will I think solve that
issue
and so if you were to do it is that
issue on the data frame or on the Altera
chart oh I guess I thought it was on the
chart I may have misunderstood
um
okay and you make the chart you're able
to specify like Altair is guessing is
this a quantitative scale is this a
nominative scale is this an ordinal
scale alterable guess based on the data
but if it ever gets confused it has a
little shorthand method where you tell
it this is nominative data this is
quantitative data which would be a queue
for instance
yeah and and that is a really important
trick
um that comes in when you're like
um so you can import a data frame to
Altair but you can also just pull
directly
um like a URL to
um to like a CSV file that's stored
somewhere else
um but when you do that um you don't
have the sort of pre-processing
capability that pandas adds
um so if you're pulling in a data frame
or if you're pulling in a CSV from
somewhere else Altair doesn't do the
work to figure out what columns are are
what types
um so if you're doing that you do
actually have to declare the column type
um every time
um so you know as as a sort of best
practice
um it is good to get into the habit of
that so when you run into it
um you do sort of remember so let's
let's just throw in a colon and a Q on a
mount
um and that that's a quantitative value
the n is for nominal so like you're
categorical
um or ordinal
um value we'll go into that is just a
string
um there's also T which is temporal
um there's one other
but I don't remember it right now
um yeah so if you do run into an issue
where uh where Altair is giving you like
uh uh um yeah encoding is special
specified without a type error
um just remember that if you declare the
variable type that will usually resolve
that
um great so then we have our uh color
um
encoding and we just want to color it by
the committee position so let's pop that
in
position
and so now it'll just pick arbitrarily
from its default uh color uh color set
um it'll just like
assign one category to
um
uh to one of the colors you can override
that
um using those sort of more
um the using that Altair
um kind of syntax that gives you some
more options
um but otherwise it'll just assign it a
default thing
um and as you'll notice it'll also give
you that little Legend there
um
and uh so we're like we're like 90 of
the way there
um
we could uh
we could add a um properties function
onto the end of this chart
um and properties will let you access
the sort of like more higher level
um higher level kind of functions
um like assigned to the Chart so
um not specifically like data encoding
related but for example
um the title of the chart
um and let's just call this
um top contributor
your title case
um
[Music]
64.
so if we were actually printing this
we'd probably want a um title that kind
of uh gives people a little more
background on like what proposition 64
is
um but in this case we'll just go with
that
um this area is also where you would
specify
a custom width so if we want this chart
to be like a little bit wider
600 look at this
um and that that will actually
um I believe alter the width of the
chart so then anything else will kind of
be tacked onto the sides
um
and we could do the same with height
say 500 nice big chart
there
um
yep uh no just uh sorry um yeah first
yeah absolutely let's shipment um I just
want to kind of uh we've got a couple
folks kind of run into some issues where
I think like uh
it's it's important to note that like uh
even though like this was uh Andrea's
like like see it looks like she's
starting a new section here essentially
like you don't need to like start the
process from scratch on your ends
um and we should have like made that
super super clear at the outset
essentially like like you should you
know the whole point is uh or super
helpful to keep like that terminal
window open that we were using before
and keep like everything in place
essentially because since we're working
with a the end or virtual environment
like
if you exit terminal or close terminal
window you essentially have to redo a
bunch of steps and so like in order we
should have explicitly said this but
basically like you wanna you wanna just
rely on the same stuff that we had
already done earlier and not close stuff
out and start another start another
session you don't need to do that
um
I I also wonder maybe uh when you're
when once you as you said ship it like
once we get there like I also kind of
feel like just maybe a recap of like the
steps that we took might be might be
useful for folks
uh for for the chart specifically or the
for like everything the chart the charts
um yeah I think but yeah
unless somebody else wants to speak up I
just think it might be
a little helpful
yeah
um yeah so
we
yeah we started with this this top
contributors data frame
um and we made this like kind of Fairly
fairly straightforward
um pretty
kind of like chart but we're
um again truncating our our data frame
um a little bit so we're not showing
every single data point we're just
showing kind of the top things
um we did uh decide to make it a bar
chart
um but I can't spell line uh we could
just we could have made a line chart
doesn't really make sense in this
context but that is where you might say
like um
The Marked circles
um
so we made it we decided to make a bar
chart
um
and then once we had decided on those
sort of like uh overriding
um values we just had to give it some
data
um and that's basically like passing in
those columns
um
to uh to like where we want Altair to
show them
um so we picked uh a name for the
y-axis
um which is the vertical axis
and the uh the amount donated to the
x-axis and again you can
you can play around with that so you can
always switch those back
if you have a reason to prefer
those values on a particular axis
um
and then we did um create that new
column name
um so we are actually now using
um the kind just the full name rather
than the last name
um and that gives us a little bit better
kind of a little bit of a more
um like readable
um
visualization
and
uh and then we added in color
um to show whether someone was actually
donating that money
um to a pose or support
um the proposition
um where we are maybe interested in
Julie's shower so it's interesting to
kind of maybe show her in the context of
the top donors
um
and then
we can hit this little uh this little
menu
um that's always going to be at on the
right side of your
um of yourself
entire chart
um and we can export
um our to another format so
um to say you can save it as a PNG and
that would just give you an image
um you can say that as an SVG and that
would let you open it in Adobe
Illustrator and make some changes
um Altair almost never
um Altera doesn't always export give you
sort of the like prettiest defaults
um
so you can uh you know you you may not
want to go like all the way to fully
mind in Altair
um there is a lot that you can do to
kind of pass in additional styling
things but sometimes it's easier to just
pop it out and edit it in
English the colors to your house colors
um you can also open
um this in the Vega editor
um and this is where Altair's power like
really comes into play so Altera is
actually a oh my mouse just died
um so Altair is actually just like an
overlay onto a JavaScript library called
Vega
um or Mega light
um they're sort of two
um
two different variants of the same
Library
um
and and the Vega specification is and
you do not need to know any of this
um really to to use it
um but the Vegas specification is in um
Json which is a JavaScript which is
Javascript object notation
um and it'll you can you can kind of go
through a Vega chart and see it setting
all those things that we did in Python
so we can see
um
uh you know it the mark Barr
um that encoding the color is a nominal
a categorical variable
um that acts as a quantitative variable
that Y is a nominal variable we passed
in those customs
and uh and width and title things you
can actually edit those here and
um see those see changes so
um
we wanted to change that to 65 we could
and it would show up right on that chart
um
but from here you sort you actually have
a JavaScript thing you could um you
could pull the Vega
um library and put that on the page
um with this Vega light configuration
um and you could have a chart
um so uh if you if you wanted to do like
an interactive chart you could do that
from here
um
and you wouldn't have to mess with any
of this stuff because you did it all in
a python notebook
um
but to that end
um you can actually so because you can
actually
um end up kind of exporting to a uh a
JavaScript
um like thing that you could embed
somewhere else
um
we can add interactive elements to this
chart that we have now
um and the sort of the thing that is
really nice for exploratory
visualization
um so like when we're just starting to
look at the data we just like want to
know what all the sort of uh columns
associated with Sean Parker's
organization are
um
we can add another encoding called tool
tip
um and then into that encoding we can
pass any of the column names that we
actually want to show on a tool test
um
so we'll want to do the full name
contributor full name we can't actually
see the full name uh in this chart right
now so that uh so that might be kind of
a way if you have really long strings
um sometimes that's a good way to
um see them if they're getting truncated
in your chart
um
amount and then we probably do also want
that committee position
and so when you run it you shouldn't see
anything change but when you hover over
each bar you will now you should now see
a tool tab
um and you may also uh one thing that
does crop up is that sometimes the
tooltip command for some reason has a
harder time
um like assigning variables to
um two types so
um if you're running into weird errors
there
or overall generally good practice to
just always throw in the type of
variable
um
and there are also some way there are
also like ways that you can format that
tool tip so you could pass in
um kind of a formatter function and get
the amount with like a dollar sign and
commas for the thousands
um which makes it a little easier to
read but um in this kind of quick
quick
um run down we don't necessarily need
that
um and then the last thing is that if
you
um
if you have this chart and you really
just sort of want to make
you want to put it into Data wrapper you
don't actually you just want to use
Altair to like look at your look at your
data kind of uh
uh
at first but you don't you don't really
want to go on and and kind of export the
Altair chart and put that into your kind
of
send that to your graphics team or if
you're the graphics team you don't you
don't necessarily want to kind of throw
that up on your story
um what you can also do
and we just if you recall looked at the
top 10
um contributors uh so
um what you can do there is just say to
CSC
and then give it a name file name like
top contributors dot CSV
um and if you run that it will save out
a CSV and actually we can check that out
um in this in our file browser you
should now actually just see
um uh CS just saved out
um
we can open it too
um it does it will save the index
um the index
by default
um that those uh
those index numberings that we don't
really care about
um you can turn that off by passing in
index equals false
um then we get a new
CSV
um great so so we just exported that to
a CSV from here you could grab that CSV
and put it into Data wrapper or flourish
if you want to
um kind of if you if your Newsroom uses
a specific
um tool and you don't actually want to
use the Altair
um chart if you want to uh export that
whole data set also you don't need to
just
um just output that uh head
um command you can just grab the whole
thing and that will give us everything
with the new column we've added this is
a grouped data set so we have kind of
manipulated it
um
uh so that will give you something that
you can kind of then go on to your next
step
um with
um or you can take this chart and uh pop
it up on your website
um and of course you can also uh like
actually go to your
erasing that
there we go
um so you can actually go into your
finder and find that CSV file and that
is saved out for you to open in Excel or
anything else
um
and yeah I think that is uh that's kind
of the the quick intro to Altair
um there's a lot of other stuff that you
can do with Altair
um
and uh
uh and their documentation is extremely
good so
um it has like
um
uh so they have like a ton of
um examples that you can just pull from
and pop them into your
charts into your
um notebook
you can make maps
um but basically anything you might want
to do there's there's going to be an
example that'll get you like at least 60
of the way
um
and uh
and then you can experiment from there
um so I think that is
all the charting that we've got
questions about Altair
I have a quick aesthetic question
um so on the X and Y axes just the
labels there just by default the
variable names with the underscore is
there and you change that without having
to change the variable name or is it
just easy to export it to illustrator or
D3 or something like that and work with
it that's a great question
um yes it is
um
um I think it's just title yep so we can
just add title and if we like this is
top contributors we sort of know what
that y-axis is we don't necessarily need
to say that again
um so I think we could just say title
none
it'll remove it
um if we wanted to label that x-axis alt
dot X
um
contribution amount
um then we got a nice much more uh
readable
um
we can even do the same thing with with
that uh label
so
for the legend
um amazing thank you just one quick
follow-up
um so the data set
um are we just not
is there no risk of the negative amounts
because we're assuming that any negative
amount is also supplemented by a
positive amount for the return donations
or is there a risk that the negative
numbers could alter
um
the the chart somehow
depends what you're trying to do with
the analysis I would say in most cases
you do want to subtract the refunds from
your accounts because because the money
was given back you know I so I think for
the purpose of like who gave the most I
think that generally most refunds you're
going to want to x out you know allow to
cancel out I think where it could come
in is like let's say you're doing a
count of contributions right that would
it's actually two records in the table
and they they cancel each other out but
they would count as two checks if you
just did a standard count and so it kind
of depends on what analysis you're
trying to do right and then if it's a
gigantic refund you might want to figure
out what the heck happened you know and
so I think when you really dig it into a
prop you're probably going to want to
look at those refunds and really get a
good grip on what the heck was going on
you know yeah that makes sense thank you
so much this was amazing thanks to all
of you
the other thing I'd add there is just
like
knowing as much as you can about how the
data set is created
um that's not a technical thing but just
like making sure if you do see refunds
that you know why those are in there and
what they mean
um is really really interviewing the
data and interviewing the people who
know the data yep
and there's five or six things like that
about campaign finance that every
campaign Finance person has to learn and
that nobody really tells you you know
the UN itemized is a big one the refunds
is another right
um there's a few other things kind of in
that ballpark as well
um like a common thing in California is
that committees will will pass money
around between committees there's
committee to committee transfers which
some people call the washing machine for
good reason and there's a way in which
when you're analyzing a proposition you
can double count money if you just look
at incoming money to a a committee
because it potentially could have come
from one committee and then into another
committee and to count it twice would be
to double count the actual dollars right
if it was an internal transfer within
the sort of cause so there's things like
that
that are bugaboos that are out there in
every state and in every system
um another thing in California is a
committee can support more than one
ballot measure or oppose more than one
ballot measure like a union might raise
a bunch of money for two or three ballot
measures it's very common and but it's
only one piggy bank and so it's actually
impossible to know how much money was
raised or spent for any of the
individual propositions because they're
just like in one big kind of fund
and so there's so like when you're
trying to rank which prop got the most
money or whatever it's sometimes
actually impossible due to flaws in the
accounting system
aren't you glad you asked
sorry to go on and on what else do folks
want to know I feel like I want to thank
all my other teachers Iris and Andrea
our coaches Cheryl Joe and Derek but I
also just want to hang on the line and
take any and all questions that anybody
has
um because you know that's why we're
here what do folks want to know
hey um just a couple quick questions
first off thank you guys so much this
was um a treasure I really appreciate it
uh
because I noticed there was myself and I
think of some other people are having
trouble
um maybe not trouble but like switching
from the terminal editor and then back
to yeah the python notebook can be kind
of a two-step dance uh I I noticed in
the bottom left and it's on mine and it
was on yours when you screencraft there
it seems like there's a way to open up a
terminal from the the python notebook
there is you're right there is so are we
able to then install like if you didn't
want to do that song and dance of like
going to your outside Terminal which you
can obviously do or something could you
install your python modules from that
terminal so you could just like keep it
all in one space you know I actually
think you could
Iris does this more than me that that
would work wouldn't it yeah
oh sorry
you can also maybe we should teach it
that way in the future
I just have never been a heavy user of
the terminal in the notebook but I
believe that you're correct and that
might be a better way to teach it to be
honest
another thing you can do and this is
this is applies for people using Google
collab categorically is
um you can do a command in the cell that
begins with exclamation mark then
everything after that is that as if you
typed in the terminal it's called a
shell a camera with the way the title is
but so um
so in collab the only way you can
install their libraries is do
exclamation mark pip install
you don't have to do Altera because it's
already in there but the ones that don't
come already in collab you don't do pip
and you do just pip
um but the way that works you could do
the same thing in the exercise the way
we taught it today where you do
exclamation mark pip and install
Altair and it would run and later you'd
get an error that it didn't need to run
because it had already been done and you
could delete that but um that's another
way to sort of avoid switching between
the notebook and the terminal
um
I think both of those are great ideas
and they show people taking advantage of
some of these features um I think you
know the way we've done in the class I
think is really just a reflection of of
my personal habits and aren't
necessarily always the best or most
direct way though I do think ultimately
there is no escaping the command line
and you have to kind of make your peace
with it
yeah it's it's good to just get
comfortable with it they're um
I feel like I haven't seen them well I
shouldn't remember there being some
decent tutorials around like getting
comfortable in it but I'd have to go
hunting for references
um sorry go ahead Derek I can ask you
later okay I'm sorry
um I was just curious so we've covered
the pandas and and Altair are there any
other kind of data analysis packages
that are just really well known that we
shouldn't be aware of that we haven't
really covered
Andrea what would you say
um wait sorry I was I was he was asking
what are other what are other like
important python data packages people
should look into besides the ones we
covered
hmm
I think I mean some of the ones I
actually some of the things I use the
most are like
um
there's like busy data and
um like CSV kit things you can use on
the command line to like check out your
data and kind of
um
uh examine it before you fire up a whole
Jupiter or notebook
um and often like if I just need to vet
a data set and it's like not it's
crashing Excel or whatever that's that
can be a really useful way to
um
kind of check it out before before you
get to the kind of analysis stage
um and run some some summaries and do a
little cleaning sometimes
not usually great to do cleaning on that
end so I think there's things related to
web scraping are really important we
didn't get to so the requests library to
just grab a URL and the Beautiful soup
library or some of its competitors to
like parse a web page and pull data out
of it those are both really crucial
learning scraping is huge
um on kind of the high end this is stuff
that I I don't really teach and I'm only
a newbie using really I think is going
to be stuff like the natural language
processing and machine learning toolkits
that are in Python like the nltk and
scikit I mean they're the The Cutting
Edge of Open Source when it comes to
you know artificial intelligency kind of
stuff and you know we've used them from
time to time actually to clean and
classify campaign Finance data so you've
got a hundred thousand donors to the
Bernie Sanders campaign or whatever it
is and you want to merge their names or
have a computer guess what industry
sector they work in you can train a
machine learning thing to go over the
data and kind of make its best guesses
and so like that would be an example uh
building off what we did here today
I would also say that rather than
looking for more libraries that do like
advanced stuff like getting better at
python fundamentals will really ask you
a lot because a lot of the stuff that
were like somebody mentioned this slack
like renaming uh or reordering the
columns can be a pain in the butt and it
can be but if you know a little bit of
python it can actually potentially be
really simple and I think if I recall I
shared a link to a census uh notebook
that I used for a workshop last year at
night car and just as part of doing that
notebook like I used some of those kinds
of tricks in part because I wanted to
sort of show people that
you know once you sort of understand how
python flows you can really do a lot of
things much more efficiently than you
think you could and that's probably more
important than fancy so like being able
to write a little one-liner that gets
all the columns Resorts them and then
applies that back to the data frame
right absolutely
I had a question
um about kind of organizing your
notebook if you have a very long
notebook maybe you have some functions
in there is there a way to separate and
like link notebooks or organize it that
way
yes so a notebook can run another
notebook using the the magic commands we
talked about earlier so like percentage
sign run followed by the path to a
notebook allows one notebook to execute
another so I've seen examples where
people will have like a master notebook
that executes a whole bunch of them kind
of in a string right it's like one way
to do it also you know where we were
importing these third-party libraries at
the top like pandas and all pair but you
can import your own files and so one
thing we'll often do is The Notebook
will live in a little folder and
alongside it will be like a little
utilities file and the utilities file
will have a couple things that we're
going to reuse across notebooks and
we'll just import that at the top of the
notebook
thank you
um so we we covered what the um
with the markdown uh did
and what the code did obviously what
happens with the raw uh in the drop down
menu
I can't say I've ever used it do you
guys have any utility for the Raw
cell
sometimes when I um write a code instead
of commenting out I'll put in raw
but because it's just like text and you
can just dump it there yeah
okay thank you
other questions
Katie
yeah um and this may not
um be
I don't know it might not have a simple
answer okay so I'm like a little bit
hesitant to ask but like you mentioned
that like a lot of campaign Finance
documents are still on paper and so like
if someone who was like a crazy person
wanted to go and put those in like to
um a database themselves would you use
like SQL or is there a way to do that in
Python
um I'm just like I'm curious what that
would look like this you mean when you
say this crazy person let's let's
discuss them a little more so this this
crazy person hypothetically would be key
punching them in manually or how would
they be getting it in
um yeah so that's kind of what I'm
wondering what's the most efficient way
to get data that's on paper or PDF into
um I mean this is a big problem there's
a bunch of strategies I bet Cheryl has
some ideas
uh well
I mean you can you can try to use tabula
right to extract it if it's in some kind
of structured format
um so there's that I mean I actually
think Derek will probably have more
ideas than I do because he messes with
this all the time with Precinct results
right
yeah you um
you do the data entry or pay someone
else to do it
I mean like like the the
you can there are lots of different OCR
libraries like uh that will give you
some text like it depends on how texty
it is or how numbery it is if it if
there's a lot of text involved it's
probably worth your time like uploading
it to like document cloud and just
seeing how what kind of text they dump
out just to see like if it like that's a
that's like a free OCR service for you
basically if it's like a PDF and you
upload a document cloud
uh but like regular OCR itself like uh
you know whether it's like free or paid
will get you like you'll you'll still
have to go and like verify you know go
and do either spot checks or clean up
anyway like there's no easy there's no
easy route here so
yeah yeah AP just released something at
the conference uh I was just gonna paste
it I just did it in the chat
collaborative yeah
Harvester and I'm gonna check this out
because it is something we do a lot of
right because I think there is an
element to I mean what I like to call it
focused data entry because I want to
emphasize to our team and to others that
we're not just going to enter
everything on the planet you know what I
mean that it has to be kind of focused
and so to me there is kind of an art to
a certain type of data journalism
project where you're pounding into
a spreadsheet or a database you know
what I mean and um I think limiting the
amount you have to do is key like you
know you're gonna say like Iris worked
on this one about we we put in all the
um local investigations into police
shootings from these letters this
unstructured letters from the DA's
office and to get it done it's like
we're only doing four Fields guys you
know what I mean and like you know and
if the and we're not going to try to you
know you try to limit how much you do
and then I think if you do that and then
you
you pool the work among a large
well-trained group of people
um and you do some pilot testing where
you kind of say well if we do five or
ten of them how long does it take you
like clock yourself you can kind of
budget out how bad it's going to be and
then kind of make a more informed
decision about what to do but I think if
you set that up I think a a well
manicured Google spreadsheet can get you
a long way and then I think beyond that
like a tool like Django which is a
python
database tool that allows you to create
an Administration panel with a very
small amount of configuration can be the
thing you send people into to like pound
it through and have a little more
validation and a little more
organization to it and so for us those
are kind of how we approach
focused data entry and then your pandas
can just read out of that you know what
I mean that dumps something that goes
out into the analysis
I mean we're using Django for the
California reporting project data entry
or a police disciplinary records about
that then the other piece of that
members of the team the reporters can
access the actual documents in document
Cloud so they can they can use the data
that's entered as a as their Tip Sheet
and then they can go into the documents
to do deeper reporting
and I always say you always want a
reviewer like a main entering Princeton
and then like someone else to review
just to ensure uh accuracy right I'm
really glad AP is doing this because I
think that it is it's almost like a
discipline or like a type of product
data journalism project that we haven't
really kind of like formalized maybe as
much as we should or like thought about
what are the principles and best way to
kind of do this sort of thing you know
but oftentimes I think some of the most
impactful work is that way because it's
data that's being hidden you know or
fractured
I think there's sometimes there's an
advantage to having
I I did a big Elder Care Project where
all of the reporters on the project were
doing data entry as was I
um and every having everyone know how
the data was structured and having
everyone like reading through these
massive PDFs
um so they knew what the interesting
Fields were like it took so much time
but everyone asked better questions of
the data because everyone knew how it
worked I wasn't just exporting a pivot
table and like giving it to them yeah
that was an air table you might have to
be crazy
yeah
the
uh data entry project would you have to
add some sort of disclaimer explaining
that there could be errors because the
data was manually entered or what's the
process behind that
I mean you try to be transparent about
how you did it and you try to make sure
you minimize those before it goes out
but to us it's just kind of yeah here's
what it is
there's here's how we did it and you try
to you know
that is why you do double entry though
so that the double entry then you you
flag the discrepancies and then you go
back and check and see what's going on
so you can try to get a pretty high
level of accuracy yep and then a lot of
using say a tool like pandas to like
turn the data 10 different ways and like
is there a weird outlier is something
that makes sense are things what you
know kind of what they should be you
know really can help
but in short there's no shame in
building your own database and in fact
if you build the database that's a sign
that you're probably going to get a
scoop because nobody else is totally
worked yet yes and there's no shame in a
great database and great story having a
small imperfection you know we have to
live with that sometimes
I have a question if I had one of the
weird errors from earlier uh to get
Panda to run what should I do after this
to try and get this was the pandas pip
install thing with the weird numpy
warning yes
I think your your teachers are going to
do a little research to see if we can
replicate this bug ourselves and uh and
and come up with what the fix is my plan
is when we get the video up on YouTube
to send an email to everybody who signed
up for the class you know what I mean
and if we can figure it out by then I'll
try to include that message I'll try to
include what we think is the solution in
that message does that sound okay yeah
that sounds good
if you figure it out let us know this is
a new one for us okay
a couple folks uh on the side that uh
news nerdy is like a place where people
in our field help each other and so
um also like just jump on there and I
mean depending on how in depth the
problem is it may be take some time to
sort of schedule and find someone who
can help you out with it but there's a
lot of people who like to help there
right yeah I bet if we asked in that
python Channel somebody might know and
and what the other thing I would say
essentially like I encourage you to I
mean it's frustrating for sure but I
encourage you to try and figure it out
essentially but when you do that like
the best help the best thing you can do
to help yourself is to keep a log of
what you tried
and and like every command you tried
just copy it like when you enter it copy
it into some other document or whatever
just be like I tried this in this order
because that will actually be meaningful
to like like the reason why a lot you
know like we weren't always able to
solve stuff today is that like well one
reason like we're not sitting in the
same room and I can't just walk we can't
just walk over and look over your
shoulder to see what you're doing the
other thing is like
like
despite like like it's hard to get like
full context remotely
um and so like there are things that
like even despite like your best efforts
and our questions like we're still gonna
miss those things we're not gonna get
and so the best thing you can do for
yourself and for others is to like be
like here's exactly what I tried and
this is and then this was the outcome
and then I'd be like okay well I I now I
can now sort of try to replicate like
what you went through and see if I get
the same outcome right and so like
that's helpful totally and there's
actually a terminal command that can
help with this there's one that's called
history if you just type history and hit
enter it will spit out your last umpteen
number of commands in order and you can
see what you ran
you can even analyze it see which
commands you run most often
other questions
maybe make an Altair chart out of it
there you go
who am I number one with the bullet
I have a question about go ahead
I have a question about installations so
it seems like you know pandas and alter
those seem like things that we have to
install every time we uh fire up a new
Jupiter notebook but what about Jupiter
lab itself is that something that is now
on my computer and I can fire up a new
one anytime I want or is that something
I need to install every time it's only
inside that one virtual environment okay
right so uh so when you when we did the
Pippi NV install it's sort of creating
that little self-contained module which
is local to that folder so the folder we
made first python notebook is sort of
secretly connected to like a a a box of
installed stuff that's like Elsewhere on
your computer and so if you're in that
folder and you do pippy and B run it's
going to have access to those things if
you're in a different folder it's not
and so the way we taught in class today
every time you started a new project you
would do a new Pipi and B and a new set
of installs right got it which is going
to result in having maybe a bunch of
different versions of the stuff on your
computer it's my view that you're better
off in the long run if you do that
um people prefer to have like a global
installation and that is possible if you
look it up you can find ways to do that
where you you install one Jupiter lab
for forever
um some people will make one repository
that just has a hundred notebooks in it
you know there's different ways to
organize things and they're not right or
wrong but I'm just a big fan of trying
to because we have to juggle so much you
know like in our Newsroom it's like you
know in the course of a year I might
have 50 to 100 repositories you know and
so it's nice to be able to just have
things be discreet
you know yeah Tupperware method yes yeah
like it does like if as Ben says it you
do wind up with like multiple
environments like laying around your
computer but the which you might seem
like a little bit of a mess but the
reason the only reason like not to do
that is if you trust yourself fully to
do the right thing with your computer
all the time and I've been doing this
for 20 some years and
I'm not even close to that point yet
like I literally do not trust myself
enough to do system-wide installs and
depend on everything working like uh you
know it creates a little sandbox for you
and that sandbox is so that you can
screw things up and not kill everything
else you've got going on right but I
mean then these tools have a bunch of
bugs and they suck and that's like the
downside you know so it's not perfect
either and I think this is why to be
honest with you I think this is a reason
why R has is really popular with a lot
of beginners is because you download it
you double click it you got the thing
you know what I mean and the thing's
there right and like I get it you know
what I mean that's cool
like my dream is that that's going to be
in the cloud is that the next generation
of tools like Google collab and Jupiter
are going to be like part of your GitHub
account and you could make a new
repository in GitHub and boom just have
a notebook like right in there that's
kind of my dream I think we will have
that in in the next decade or something
but we're not quite there yet well I'm
where you I mean like but Simon Willison
is doing with data set is you know is
pretty interesting and we're actually
integrating that with big local news so
that people can just do their analysis
from any data in that in a whatever
project right there right they just open
it up they do their analysis they share
the URLs whatever their analysis is with
whomever like that I so I think that's
an example kind of what you're talking
about man yeah
phase I just wanted to say that Ben is
right that things have bugs and they can
be frustrating but also all this stuff
is really methodical and it does what
you tell it to do and so somebody said
thanks Wizards in the chat and I
appreciate that but I really want people
to not think that this is magical and
not think that when things don't work
it's because they're buggy and it's
frustrating and you know those of us
that are teaching have been doing this
for a long time
but it it bet you it pays off to like
recognize as methodical and to try and
sort of develop the patience and you
know and we like to help people because
we know we got that help from people
before but
um you know it's it's a systematic thing
yeah and I really think you know
our work is getting more and more
specialized and more and more advanced
and I think that to really
be a data journalist who is the
specialist who does this stuff you just
have to learn the terminal you have to
learn this it's like there's not
really a way around it but it's true
that it's not wizard Wizardry right it's
just a matter of like it's just learning
it and it's kind of like you know you'd
be a data journalist I think kind of
like a crotcheted copy editor right they
know all the rules they know all the
things no you have to spell them up you
just spell it that way well we just have
to learn you just learn the various code
which I'm not very good at but yeah I
can also Google it and find the answer
and I you know I can get there
other questions and like yeah feeling
frustrated and running into errors is
like it's not because you're not good at
it it's because it's part of the thing
like I spend like half of the time I'm
trying to do anything really frustrated
and frantically Googling
um but like
that's sort of part of it and you get a
lot better at Googling for the right
things
um and like troubleshooting
um but it's not supposed to work
perfectly
yeah so it's not it's not a reflection
on your your skills necessarily yeah you
said that I did love to see to be honest
with you data journalists take on the
responsibility for improving these tools
you know what I mean rather than just
always being open source users being
open source contributors and maintainers
and helping you you know we've seen that
with Altair and other things
CSV kit invented by a journalist so I'll
tell you another tool that we're we're
building
if you're interested and that's a fips
it's a fips tool that allows you to
um if you have a bunch of County names
you can add you you use our fips tool
which is not yet deployed but it will be
uh and it will add in all of the fips
codes for all your counties so so like
yeah just little tiny things that will
make it easier
you got a name for it
I can't remember the explosion
kind of like fipsomatic that's kind of
fun
we have another one called the labeler
we're working on
it's like if you have a bunch of things
that are like he's got like cherry
banana broccoli you start
create creating a label sorry
fruit vegetable fruit vegetable you do
the first 10 rows or whatever
then you run that tool and it will auto
populate and you still want to go
machine learning for the masses that's
the idea we're not there yet but we're
getting there we're close
sounds like Stanford
anyone else have questions
uh yes uh is it okay if I share my nut
book with you and ask questions because
I cannot find where I took a mistake
um my my table uh doesn't seem the same
as yours and the uh if I uh when I check
are you in the the news nerdery slack uh
yeah yes I I've just joined the you were
so your notebook is just a file like any
other file and so if you were to join
our Channel which is fpn nikar 21 yes
and just upload your notebook into there
I think we'd be happy to look at it and
give you some feedback thank you
other questions
uh if no one else has had any others uh
if I could be greedy and maybe ask one
more uh please as long as long as no one
else had one uh then I know you
mentioned earlier
um that and I went to uh the demo that
um Simon Wilson and your colleague Ryan
Murphy did on get scraping which was
brilliant um and really cool and they
mentioned something that you mentioned
that uh you run a lot of the Python
notebooks some of them like automated
through through goodscaping
um totally okay if this is not open
source or Publishers you guys already
give so much I feel like to the
community is it are is that code because
I'm I'm trying to maybe eventually work
in like automated runs of these of these
totally python notebooks is that open
open a small portion of it is and I hope
to gradually make more of it so we have
kind of a demonstration repository on
GitHub it's called California
coronavirus scrapers and it has two
Jupiter notebooks that are that have
Tableau scrapers that are run via the
GitHub action
um the notebooks are pretty standard
scraping with the few Tableau Smash and
grab that kind of hits
um the trick of of scheduling it is uh
is running the notebook from the shell
which is just much much too hard and one
of my personal open source goals is to
help write the notebook shell script
Runner I want to make that happen
um but in that repository you'll find a
file called run.py which is basically
the file we used to call and invoke a
note from the shell and run it which the
action just like literally just runs
that one line of code to run the
notebook basically
what you see in there is exactly what
runs inside our system and I actually
want to gradually move more of them out
there because it's also free yeah and we
can then we can then pull the data in
our system without the cost either
yeah just really really cool stuff like
definitely gonna help me
um a lot so I really appreciate it I
think I think that in the last year
we've seen a lot of GitHub action
Innovation blocked up inside newsrooms
and I one of one of my goals for this
year too is to help try to open that up
and see what other patterns people have
and learn from each other and my hope
would be is that the next night car we
have a class called first GitHub action
or first GitHub scraper and we we teach
that as part of a class would be my hope
any other questions
okay hearing none I'm going to adjourn
this call I want to thank again my
fellow teachers Iris Lee and Andrew
suozo our coaches Cheryl Joe Derek Sean
green who's out there somewhere it's
been helping people along the way quite
modestly as well hello hey Sean
and um thank you to everyone who came
and and you know spent your time on this
I hope it was worth it to you remember
the whole class is scripted so you can
go back over it again if you have
thoughts on how we might improve it or
change it for the future we definitely
want to hear it you um you know uh you
can feel free to email us or message us
on news nerdery
um we want you know this class has
evolved quite a bit the last few years
and we want to continue to improve it to
make it better and better and you know
your feedback is the best way to do that
um thank you